<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rose, and lily Delivered at the lecture, in Ashby de-la-zouch in the county of Leicester. By William Parks, Master of Arts, and curat of Chelaston in the county of Derby.</title>
            <author>Parks, William, curat of Chelaston.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 217 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 101 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72989</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19303.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124820</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898715</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898715</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152100</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72989)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152100)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2013:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rose, and lily Delivered at the lecture, in Ashby de-la-zouch in the county of Leicester. By William Parks, Master of Arts, and curat of Chelaston in the county of Derby.</title>
                  <author>Parks, William, curat of Chelaston.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 48, [2], 41, [5], 44, [4], 41, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.N. for George Wilne, and are to be sold by Samuel Man at the signe of the the [sic] Swan in S. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In four parts, each with separate pagination and register.</note>
                  <note>Sub tpp cancelled.--STC.</note>
                  <note>Copy filmed at UMI microfilm Early English Books 1475-1640 reel 2013 lacks pages 8 and 9.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College Library, Dublin.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152100:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152100:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ROSE, AND LILY. DELIVERED AT THE <hi>LECTVRE, In</hi> ASHBY de-la-Zouch <hi>in the County of</hi> Leiceſter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> WILLIAM PARKS, <hi>Maſter of Arts, and Curat of</hi> Chelaſton <hi>in</hi> the County of DERBY.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Diſcendum propter docendum.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by J. N. for GEORGE WILNE, and are to be ſold by SAMUEL MAN at the ſigne of the the Swan in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1640.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:152100:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152100:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the Right Honourable <hi>HENRY</hi> Earle of <hi>Huntingdon,</hi> Lord <hi>Haſtings, Hungerford, Botreaulx, Molins</hi> and <hi>Moules,</hi> and Lord Lieutenant of his <hi>Majeſtes</hi> County of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> and <hi>Rutland,</hi> my Honoured <hi>Lord.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right HONOVRABLE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not any want of Bookes in theſe daies of ours, wherein they doe ſo much abound, that moves mee to publiſh theſe my weake labours, nor yet any deſire I have to ſhew myſelf
<pb facs="tcp:152100:3"/>in <hi>Print,</hi> J am too ſenſible of mine owne imperfections, to be deſirous to ſhew them to the World. But conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering my engagments (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to your <hi>Honour</hi>) and not willing to be altogether guilty of that hatefull ſinne of ingratitude, but know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no other way to expreſſe my thankefulnes J have pitched upon this, chooſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rather to ſhew my ſelfe a weake man, then ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. J muſt confeſſe I had rather beſilent, then be ſeen in <hi>Print.</hi> And my ſmall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, had made me as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected in perſon as J was in place, untill it pleaſed your
<pb facs="tcp:152100:3"/>
               <hi>Honour</hi> to caſt the beames of your countenance on mee (in giving mee part of this <hi>Lecture</hi> where theſe <hi>Sermons</hi> were preached) which made me a little <hi>erigere caput,</hi> to peepe up, and ſhew my ſelfe, if to no other end then this (to expreſſe my thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes it were a ſufficient cauſe to move mee to it. J have heere endevoured to give unto your <hi>Honour</hi> not only what <hi>Aeſchines</hi> gave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Socrates (me ipſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>)</hi> but even <hi>Deum ipſum:</hi> for it is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folding of ſome part of thoſe Myſteries that concerne <hi>Chriſt;</hi> of whom your <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> is a livelie member in
<pb facs="tcp:152100:4"/>his <hi>Church</hi> militant, and will be untill you are a full par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of all his benefits in the <hi>Church</hi> triumphant, which that your <hi>Honour</hi> may be is the prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips dayly <hi>Orator,</hi> and moſt humbly devoted Chaplaine. WILLIAM PARKES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:152100:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Praeface to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Will uſe no Praeface but onely ſay as <hi>Ruffinus</hi> did to <hi>Laurentius</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Interopa Cyp. haebetur pag. <hi>543.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>Mihi quidem ad ſcribendum animus tam non eſt cupidus, quam nec Idoneus, ſcienti non eſſe abſque periculo, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum judiciis ingemum ten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e &amp; exile committere.</hi> And indeed when I firſt pend theſe ſermons, I did not intend to put them to the Preſſe, nor to expoſe my ſelfe and them to (that which the World is too full of) cenſure. But finding ſome part of it in the delivering of them (as namely for the ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of fathers in <hi>Latine</hi> in my Sermons, &amp;c.) for which I have beene traduced be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde my back, and perſwaded to my face to leave them, I could therefore doe no leſſe (for the juſtifying of my ſelfe and the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying
<pb facs="tcp:152100:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>of others) then commit them to the eye, as I did to the eare, to ſee whether they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue any Pragmaticall cenſure. It is a true obſervation of <hi>Macrobius</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Lib. <hi>6.</hi> Satur</note>, that <hi>Multa ignoramus, quae no laterent, ſi vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum lectio nobis eſſe familiaris,</hi> wee are ignorant of many things which would not be hid unto us, if the reading of ancient writers were familiar with us, yet ſuch is the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor of ſome, that nothing can pleaſe them except it be plaine and delivered <hi>ex tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore,</hi> from mens owne braynes, without any ground or light from any ancient fathers. Though <hi>nullum eſt jam dictum quod non dictum ſit prius</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Terent Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch. prolog.</note>, There is no new thing under the Sunne<note n="d" place="margin">Eccles. 1.9.</note>: yet ſuch is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of theſe <hi>Athenians</hi> that they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together for novelties, which makes their itching eares to be delighted with new fang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led teachers, which preach the Chymaeraes of their owne braynes, altogether neglecting the fathers of the Church. If Prayers or Sermons be pend, they are preſently ſleigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the more paynes are taken in them,
<pb facs="tcp:152100:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>the leſſe acceptance have they with theſe men. I know no reaſon he had to teare out the <hi>Athanaſian Creed</hi> out of his bible; when it was read in the Church, but onely to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfy his owne humour, and as little that our <hi>Noveliſts</hi> have to except against our Church liturgy, except it bee for that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage: from all blindnes of heart, from pride, vaine glory, and hypocriſy, from envy, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and malice, and all uncharitablenes! Good Lord deliver us: which is a great part of their Religion. And I know leſſe reaſon for any to cenſure ſo raſhly, as to ſay, that a pend Sermon never converted ſoule: for I dare preſume to maintaine, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have beene converted by reading, and I thinke it muſt bee pend before it be prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and written before it be read. Wee read in the <hi>Goſpell</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">John. 3.</note>: that Christ turned water into wine, hee might as eaſily have filled the veſſells with wine, as made them to bee filled with water first: but to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy that hee will not fill thoſe empty veſſells, that come unfurniſhed into the pulpit, and
<pb facs="tcp:152100:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>looke then for Revelations. But if it were lawfull at other times to preach <hi>quicquid in buccam venerit,</hi> yet is it very unfit for a Lecture in Divinity, for a Lecture doth conſist of a mixt auditory, and must have as well meat as milke, that the learned may have strength by the one as the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant have growth by the other. Againe a Lecture (as I conceave) was at the first founded for the explayning of the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall poyntes of Religion, and the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of controverſies in the <hi>Univerſity,</hi> and ſo are continued by men of great lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and eminence, the publique profeſſors. And in Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes (as I conjecture) Lectures were permitted in <hi>Parochiall</hi> Churches, not commanded or injoyned (for I read of <hi>Parſons, Vicars,</hi> and <hi>Curates</hi> in the booke of common Prayer but not of a Lecturer) neither were they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to this end to draw eare-Chriſtians and lip-profeſſors together to parlee in a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of poynts of Divinity which they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not, and of matters of Church
<pb facs="tcp:152100:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>diſcipline that doe not concerne them, but to build the people up in knowledge, and to handle matters of controverſy, and then in points of controverſy, and explicating of difficult points of Divinity, the fathers are very fit to bee urged.<note place="margin">Ob.</note> But it is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne tongue, and the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſayth<note n="f" place="margin">1 Cor. 14 24</note>: that edifyes not, and therefore <hi>Latin</hi> is not fit to bee uſed. I anſwer,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> it edifyes the learned if not interpreted, but if interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it edifyes the Church<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aret in</hi> 1. Cor. 14.</note>, and if it were unlawfull to ſpeake in an unknowne tongue altogether, why ſhould <hi>S. Pauls</hi> practice contradict his precept? for hee writes to the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Hebrewes</hi> in <hi>Greeke,</hi> when <hi>Latin</hi> was the language of the one, and <hi>Hebrew</hi> the language of the other.<note place="margin">Ob.</note> But it takes up a great deale of time,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> Not ſo much time as many uſually spend in vaine Tautologies, and idle repetitions, which ſtand like ciphers to fill up empty places in their <hi>Sermons.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ob.</note> But it would pleaſe better without them.<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> Indeed if a <hi>Lecturer</hi> were to live like the poore and the blind meerely
<pb facs="tcp:152100:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>by collection, then happily hee must preach to pleaſe his good Maſters: or elſe hee would looſe a great part of his living. But <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> are not to be made as ſome <hi>Commae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> made their Playes. <hi>Populo ut pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerent quas feciſſent fabulas</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Terence.</note>, And yet (for ought I know) <hi>Sermons</hi> with <hi>Latin</hi> in them may pleaſe as well (and better) as thoſe without it.<note place="margin">Ob.</note> But S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe bids not to hearken what<note n="i" place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>18.</hi> &amp; contra Petil. lib.</note> 
               <hi>Rogatus, Donatus, vincentius, Hylary. Ambroſe</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> but what ſayth the Lord? But S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtines</hi> purpoſe is not<note n="k" place="margin">Hooker <hi>Eccl. Pol. lib.</hi> 2.6, 7.</note> (I thinke) when he bids us not to heare men that we ſhould ſtop our eares againſt his owne exhortation, and therefore he cannot meane ſimply; that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience ſhould be denyed unto men, but either if men ſpeake one thing, and God another, then he, not they is to be obeyed, or if they both ſpeake one thing, then alſo mans ſpeech is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of hearing, not ſimply, but in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. But Laſtly,<note place="margin">Ob.</note> it may be objected the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of themſelves are ſufficent for ſalvation and juſtification. And therefore there is no
<pb facs="tcp:152100:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>uſe of Fathers in <hi>Sermons.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anſ.</note> It is true that the Scriptures are able to make us wiſe to ſalvation: but ſuch is the dulnes of our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding that we cannot underſtand the difficult places of it without an interpretor. I confeſſe I had rather light my dim Lamp at their lights, and take an interpretation from them; then from many moderne writers, and will alwayes uſe them, and diſpiſe new <hi>non licenſed</hi> Pamphlets, that may breed facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and irregularity in the hearers. So that Fathers are not ſuch a <hi>Bugbeare</hi> but a man may looke on them without frighting, and borrow their golden ſentences, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did borrow from the <hi>Aegiptians</hi> Iewells of Silver, and Iewells of Gold. Which may appeare by example, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and <hi>Scripture.</hi> By example, thus, All the Fathers and (almoſt) all moderne writers doe it, even they themſelves that deny it will uſe moderne writers, how is <hi>Calvin</hi> urged in defence of uſury, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Church government and then why may not we cite the Fathers? By reaſon thus.
<pb facs="tcp:152100:8"/>If it bee lawfull to read them it is lawfull to cite them<note n="l" place="margin">Doctor <hi>Weſt</hi> faling in his Sermon, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at <hi>Oxford</hi> Anno. 1582.</note>, and if it be lawfull to read later writers (which I know none that doth deny) then why not them? except they may bee read for their manner of tractation, and not for their matter. By Scripture thus. The <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and our Saviour too bring ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of the <hi>Prophets</hi> in the new <hi>Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which were interpretors of the Law, and why may not wee bring ſentences of the fathers which are interpretors of the Goſpell? Nay S. <hi>Paul</hi> brings ſentences from the Poets: <hi>viz.</hi> from <hi>Aratus</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Acts 17.28.</note>: <hi>Menander</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.33.</note>. and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pimenides</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Tit. 1.12</note>: ſo that wee may rob the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Poets of their ornaments<note n="p" place="margin">Aret. loc. com. de Lect. Ethin.</note>: and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate them to Chriſt, much more may we take ſentences from the holy Fathers. Beſides there are <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Syriack</hi> words uſed in the new <hi>Teſtament</hi> without interpreting; as <hi>Anathema, Maranatha, Hoſanna,</hi> and <hi>Cephas,</hi> which might occaſion <hi>Optatus Milivitanus</hi> (for ought I know) to thinke <hi>Peter</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Lib <hi>2.</hi> contra. Parme.</note>: to bee the head of the Church hee thinking it to be a <hi>Greeke</hi> word and derived
<pb facs="tcp:152100:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a head when as it is a <hi>Sirack</hi> word and ſignifyes a ſtone: but there can bee no danger in any miſtake in urging ſentences of the Fathers being interpreted. So that though we doe not bring any grounds of faith from them, yet it is lawfull and fitting to urge them. Firſt, for interpretation of hard Texts. Secondly, for illuſtration. Thirdly, for confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of errors as our Saviour quotes<note n="r" place="margin">Mat 23.</note>: the <hi>Phariſees.</hi> Fourthly, for inſtances, and. Fift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we may uſe them comparatively, and bring the ſayings and examples of <hi>Heathen</hi> to ſhame <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> I had thought to have ſayd more, but fearing leaſt my porch ſhould be too big for my houſe, &amp; that this book ſhould be like the City <hi>Minda</hi> with too great gates, I conclude. wiſhing thee and all good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to doe that, that ſhall tend to the glory of God and the peace of the Church, <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord Jeſus. WILLIAM PARKES.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my ſtudy in Chellaſton,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>MAY. 28 1638.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="lecture">
            <pb facs="tcp:152100:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152100:9"/>
            <head>THE ROSE AND <hi>LILY.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Solomons Song. 2.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I am the <hi>Roſe</hi> of Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, and the <hi>Lily</hi> of the Valleys.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE ſumme of mans du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to God conſiſts in the keeping of the ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements which (for the brevity of them) <hi>Moſes,</hi> that man of God, calles<note n="a" place="margin">Exod 34.28.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Gnaſereth haddebarim, decem verba,</hi> ten words: our Saviour Chriſt reduceth thoſe ten
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152100:10"/>to two: and the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth thoſe two to one, when he ſayes; that<note n="b" place="margin">Galat. 5.14.</note> love is the fulfilling of the Law. But all love is not lovely in us, nor like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God: for as there is the love of God; ſo there is the love of our ſelves, and the love of the world, which two laſt, like <hi>Pharaohs</hi> leane kine<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 41.21.</note>, eat up and devour the former, and yet are never the better; and therefore they muſt bee pruned away, that the former may be grafted in. Now <hi>Solomon</hi> (who paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed<note n="d" place="margin">2 Chron. 9.22</note> all the Kings of the earth in wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) wrote three books; the booke of the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> to prune away the love of our ſelves; we muſt not thinke our ſelves to be wiſer than all others, and<note n="e" place="margin">Prov. 1.7</note> deſpiſe inſtruction leſt wee prove fooles: And the booke of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> to prune away the love of the world; becauſe<note n="f" place="margin">Eccles 1 4</note> 
               <hi>all is but vanity and vexation of ſpirit. Cum enim duo ſunt mala, quae vel ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la vel maxime militant adverſus animum, vanus ſcilicet amor mundi, et ſuperfluus
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152100:10"/>ſui; pesti vtri<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> duo illi libri obviare noſcun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">In Cant. Ser. <hi>1</hi>
               </note>. Whereas there are two evills, which either ſolely or cheifely doe fight againſt the ſoule, to wit, the vaine love of the world, and the over-weaning love of our ſelves; thoſe two Bookes yeeld a remedy for each malady: <hi>Alter ſarculo diſciplinae prava quae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in moribus, et ſuperflua carnis reſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans; alter luce rationis in omni gloria mundi fucum vanitatis ſagaciter deprehendens, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raciter<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> diſtinguens à ſolido veritatis:</hi> The one by the pruning-hooke of inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on cuts off the rudeneſſe of manners, and the ſuperfluous deſires of the fleſh; the other by the light of reaſon doth quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apprehend the ſmoake of vanity in the glory of the world, and diſtinguiſh it from the truth: And he wrote this third booke of the <hi>Canticles,</hi> to ingraffe the love of God in our hearts. As the inmoſt part of the Temple was called<note n="h" place="margin">Heb 9.3. Exod 26.34.</note> the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> the Holy of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, as being the Moſt holy place, ſo is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152100:11"/>this booke called <hi>Canticum canticorum,</hi> the Song of Songs from the excellency of it, as being the cheefeſt Song, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>Solomons</hi> (who wrote<note n="i" place="margin">1 Kings 4 23.</note> a thouſand and five) but alſo the moſt excellent Song that ever was pend, as deſcribing the union and Communion betweene Chriſt and his Church more excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and elegantly then any other. The pen-man of this booke is <hi>Solomon,</hi> which is a name of peace: he begins his booke with a<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sol. Song.</hi> 1 2.</note> kiſſe, which is a ſigne of peace: and the whole ſubject of the booke is love, which is<note n="l" place="margin">Calvin.</note> 
               <hi>fomentum pacis,</hi> the fomentation of peace; for it is a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Epithalamium,</hi> or marriage ſong up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the holy nuptialls betweene Chriſt and his Church. And although ſome (perhapps) would underſtand it literal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the marriage betweene <hi>Salomon</hi> and <hi>Pharaohs</hi> daughter: yet as our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt ſaid once,<note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 12 42.</note> a greater then <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> is here; ſo may I ſay now, a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then <hi>Solomon</hi> is here meant, and a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152100:11"/>Spowſe farr more glorious and beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, then <hi>Pharoahs</hi> daughter. As there were two <hi>Alexanders,</hi> the one <hi>Apellis o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> the other <hi>Philippi filius,</hi> the one por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed by <hi>Apelles,</hi> being unmatchable for the skilfulnes of the art, the other the ſonne of <hi>Philip,</hi> being invincible for the valour of his heart: ſo there were two <hi>Solomons,</hi> the one typricall, the other myſticall; the one the wiſeſt among the ſonns of men, and yet but a man; the other excelling all men, for he<note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 45.7.</note> was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted with the oyle of gladnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove his fellowes, being both God and man, and he it is that is chiefly ſpoken of in this booke, which ſets downe the mutuall and reciprocall love betweene him and his Church. Now the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture mentioneth<note n="o" place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erome &amp; Anſworth on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> the Bride, the Bride-Groome, and the friends of them both, and all theſe in this Song (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the two former) are brought in as ſpeakers every one of and unto others. The <hi>Text</hi> that I have choſen is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152100:12"/>the ſpeech either of Chriſt, or of the Church; for in reſpect of both it may<note n="p" place="margin">Em. Sa in l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cum.</note> be ſaid, <hi>I am the Roſe of Sharon, and the Lily of the valleys.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have all this while but ſhewed you the Trees, I ſhall now give you of the Fruit; and open the ſhell, that you may taſt the ſweetnes of the kernell: wee have hitherto, as <hi>in bortis incluſis,</hi> ſtood without, I ſhall now bring you into the Spouſes garden, where you may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Roſes, and feed on Lilies. The words conteyne three parts, Firſt, <hi>Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum,</hi> a Subject, in the firſt word, <hi>I,</hi> and that is either Chriſt, or the Church. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>Subjecti Attributa,</hi> the attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes of this ſubject, <hi>the Roſe and the Lily.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Attributorum Limitatio,</hi> the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation of theſe Attributes, <hi>the Roſe of Sharon, and the Lily of the valleys.</hi> I will begin firſt with the beſt Subject, and ſhew you wherein Chriſt doth reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>the Roſe of Sharon:</hi> for of him doe S. <hi>Hierome</hi> and others<note n="q" place="margin">Orig. Bernard Amb. Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom, et Doctor <hi>Dove</hi> in lcoum.</note> expound the Text.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:152100:12"/>
Moſt of the Fathers following the verſion of the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> in ſtead of, <hi>I am the Roſe of Sharon,</hi> read it, I am the Flower of the field; and thus S. <hi>Amb.</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Apud Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom.</note> expounds it: <hi>Ante ſuam incarnationem Salvator in Angeli perſona Patriarchis et Prophetis loquendo, ſolus cui nullusſimilis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Angelos, Thronos, Dominationes, et Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testates, omnibus admirandus, ſingularis flos in toto coelorum campo coruſcans, proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> When our Saviour ſpake to the Patriarks and Prophets in the perſon of the Angels, he ſhewed himſelfe to be the chiefe ſweet-ſmelling Flower of Heaven, having none like him among the Angels Thrones, Dominions or Powers. But, as a precious ſtone lying hid in the earth, or as a Iewell being lockt up in a casket, though it be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and beautifull in it ſelfe, yet is not beneficiall unto us, untill it be digged or taken out for our uſe; So though Chriſt were alwaies glorious in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, while he was yet <hi>in ſinu Patris;</hi>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:152100:13"/>of that which he felt at his paſſion: theſe were but dropps in reſpect of that ſhower: theſe were but skirmiſhes, in reſpect of that battaile: theſe prickles did but peirce his Skin, thoſe his Heart; theſe wounded his Body, thoſe his Soule the ſufferings of his Body, were but the Body of his ſufferings, but the ſorrow of his Soule, was the Soule of his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. Goe with him to<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 26.36.</note> 
               <hi>Gethſemane,</hi> and ſee his agony in the garden, and you ſhall ſee our propitiatory ſacrifice (though men were made upright) lye flat on the earth: he that had no place<note n="b" place="margin">Luke 9.36</note> wherein to lay his Head, could eaſily finde a place whereon to lay<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 26.39.</note> his Face, even on the ground: he that bids us to<note n="d" place="margin">Mat 11.29.</note> take his yoke on us, for it is eaſy; and his burthen, for it is light, being to take on him the yoke of our ſinns, he found it to be paynfull, and our burthen hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy: the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was<note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 3.19.</note> to eat his bread in the ſweat of his face, and the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> being to ſatiſfy for ſinne (for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152100:13"/>which that was a curſe) uſed the ſweat of his Face, and that no ordinary, but an extraordinary ſweat, even<note n="f" place="margin">Luke 22 44.</note> 
               <hi>dropps of bloud:</hi> by and by comes in <hi>Iudas</hi> that traitour, with company to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend him: he was once an Apoſtle, but he went out from <hi>Bethel</hi> to <hi>Betha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah,</hi> from the houſe of God to the houſe of confuſion, and ſold his maſter for a little money: valuing his head, at leſſe then an aſſes head was valued at, at the ſiege of <hi>Samaria,</hi> for that was ſold for<note n="g" place="margin">2 Kings 6.25</note> foureſcore peeces of ſilver, and Chriſt but<note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 26.15</note> for thirty. Goe along with him to<note n="i" place="margin">Joh. 19.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Gabbatha,</hi> and ſee his ſufferings in the high Prieſts Hall: before he comes thither, his Diſciples<note n="k" place="margin">Mat. 26.56</note> forſooke him, but <hi>Peter followed him a farr off to deny</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Luke 22.44.57.</note> 
               <hi>him:</hi> he that cured the <hi>Eyes</hi> of the blind by annoynting them<note n="m" place="margin">John 9, 6</note> with clay and ſpittle, had his own ſpit on to put them out: he was derided and was<note n="n" place="margin">Iſay 53 7.</note> dumb that had cured the dumb: though he purchaſed for us a Crowne of glory,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152100:14"/>yet was he himſelfe<note n="o" place="margin">Matth. 27.29.</note> crowned with a crowne of Thornes: the multitudes cry of<note n="p" place="margin">Mat. 21.9.</note> 
               <hi>Hoſanna,</hi> is altered and turned to <hi>Crucifige;</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Mark. 15.13.</note> crucify him: in ſtead of ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their<note n="r" place="margin">Matth. 21.8.</note> garments in his way, they part<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mat. 27.35.</note> his garments among them: hee that ſuffered for ſinners, was condemned by ſinners: the moſt righteous judge of the World, was condemned by the moſt unjuſt judge in the World; even <hi>Pilate,</hi> though he had pronounced him guiltles<note n="t" place="margin">Luke 23.22.</note> three times, will condemne himſelfe rather then not condemn him. Goe on with him to<note n="u" place="margin">John 19.17.</note> 
               <hi>Golgotha,</hi> and ſee the <hi>Catastrophe</hi> of his tragedy on Mount <hi>Calvary:</hi> and you ſhall ſee that he that ſuffered for all ſinnes, ſuffered in all his ſenſes: <hi>Sustinuit in tactu clavorum aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritatem, in auditu opprobriorum confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem, in odoratu ſputorum faeditatem, in gustu aceti et fellis amaritudinem, in oculis lacrimarum effuſionem:</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">Meſſreth Poſt. Dom. post. <hi>1.</hi> Oct. Paſch.</note> his <hi>Eyes</hi> ſaw his moſt cruell enemies, his <hi>Eares</hi> heard their bitter revilings, his <hi>Noſe</hi> ſmelt the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152100:14"/>ſtinke of the place, his taſte taſted the bitternes of the Gall and Myrrhe: his feeling felt the accuratenes of the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments he was put to. He that ſuffered for all kindes of men, ſuffered from all kindes of men, <hi>Kings, Priests, People,</hi> rich and poore, men and women. And he that ſuffered for all perſons, ſuffered in all the parts of his Body, we may<note n="x" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Auſtins</hi> meditations for good Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</note> ſay in <hi>genere</hi> (for we cannot count the ſpecies) that he ſuffered from all kinde of men all kind of payne, in every kinde of ſubject: that is, in his fame, his honour, his goods, his Soule and Body. His Head that did wear a Crowne of Majeſty, was crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>Thornes;</hi> his <hi>Eyes</hi> that were<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sol. Song.</hi> 5.12.</note> as the <hi>Eyes</hi> of <hi>Doves</hi> upon the Rivers of waters, were dazled with blowes; his <hi>Cheekes</hi> that were<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sol. Song.</hi> 5.13.</note> as a bed of Spices, and ſweet Flowers, were defiled with ſpittings, and buffetted with fiſts; his <hi>Hands</hi> that had cured diſeaſes, had now need to be cured themſelves; they that were<note n="a" place="margin">Ibid. ver. <hi>14</hi>
               </note> as rings of Gold had now rings
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152100:15"/>made in them by the <hi>Nayles:</hi> his <hi>Feete</hi> that were<note n="b" place="margin">Luke 7.38. John 11.2.</note> waſhed with <hi>Maryes teares,</hi> and wiped with the hayres of her head, were nayled to the Croſſe: we had no whole part about us by reaſon of our ſins, neither had he any whole part about him by reaſon of his ſores, but this <hi>Roſe</hi>-tree was full of prickles, from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome to the top: even<note n="c" place="margin">Eſay 1.6.</note> from the ſole of the foot to the crowne of the Head there was no ſoundnes, but wounds, and bruiſes and putrifying ſores. It is obſerved by S. <hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">De Paſſ. Dom. pag. <hi>1219.</hi>
               </note> that all that Chriſt ſuffered in the time of his exin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anition, is to be referred to the rednes of his paſſion, and the often effuſion of his bloud was the better colouring of this <hi>Roſe.</hi> Which precious bloud of his was ſhed ſeaven ſeverall times to free us<note n="e" place="margin">Deſtructo. rvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiorum.</note> from the ſeaven deadly ſins, (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from all the deady ſinens (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we were defiled. Firſt, in <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſione,</hi> when hee was circumciſed and had his name given him (that<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>l. 2.9.</note> name
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152100:15"/>above all names) to be called<note n="g" place="margin">Luke 22.1.</note> 
               <hi>Ieſus: Propterea quod tum puram ſalvationem ſanguinis fundere inciperet, qui in completi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one ſalutis nostrae totus erat effundendus,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard.</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Vbi prius.</note> Becauſe he did then begin to ſhed his bloud for our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which was wholly to be ſhed for the perfecting of it. Secondly, he ſhed his bloud in <hi>ſudore,</hi> when he ſweat drops of bloud in the Garden<note n="i" place="margin">Luke 22 44.</note>, which did not onely <hi>distillare,</hi> droppe downe <hi>guttatim</hi> drop by drop, but <hi>decurrere,</hi> it ran downe in ſo great abundance, that it was ſufficient to colour this <hi>Roſe</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly red. A third effuſion of his bloud for the colouring the <hi>Roſe</hi> of his paſſion, was in <hi>alapizatione,</hi> in his buffetting: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſay the <hi>Evangelists,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Mat. 26 67.</note> 
               <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laphis &amp; alapis caedebant eum,</hi> they buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetted him and ſmote him, and that in his <hi>Face</hi> and <hi>Neck</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Gorran in Marke chap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> with the palmes of their hands, and their fiſts ſay ſome,<note n="m" place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct. in Mat. Cap. <hi>27</hi>
               </note> or elſe with fiſts and clubs ſay other;<note n="n" place="margin">Barna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d in Conc. Eva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g Tom <hi>40</hi> lib <hi>6.</hi> Cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> ſo that it is very likely<note n="o" place="margin">Stella in Luc. Cap. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> that the bloud
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152100:16"/>flowed both from his noſtrills and mouth, though the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> expreſſe it not <hi>totidem verbis.</hi> Fourthly, his bloud was ſhed in <hi>Flagellatione,</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">John 19.1.</note> when he was ſcourged by <hi>Pilate.</hi> How great a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of bloud (thinke you) muſt flow from the moſt pure and tender Body that ever was (for, <hi>quo complexio Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lior, &amp; mens dexterior, eo tenerior eſſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let caro</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Ariſtot.</note>, the more noble the complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the more nimble the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſo much the more tender is the Skin) How much bloud (I ſay) muſt flow from this moſt tender Body, when the number of his wounds was, as<note n="r" place="margin">Ludolph. de vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Chriſti</note> ſome ſay, five thouſand fourehundred and ninety, as others<note n="ſ" place="margin">Barrad. To <hi>4.</hi> lib. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note>; five thouſand foure hundred ſeventy and five: or as others<note n="t" place="margin">Serm Meffreth de Sanct. in di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Paraſceves.</note>, five thouſand foure hundred and ſixty, according to the verſes: <hi>Sex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aginta &amp; Quadraginta ſuperaddito millia quin<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>: tot fuerat Chriſtus pro nobis vulnera paſſus.</hi> Or at the leaſt ſay they that ſay leaſt<note n="v" place="margin">Do. <hi>Gwili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams</hi> 7. Gold Candleſticks treat. of the paſſion.</note>, ſix hundred and ſixty, according
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152100:16"/>to the number of a band of ſouldiers. A 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> effuſion of his bloud was in <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tione,</hi> when<note n="w" place="margin">Mat. 27.29.</note> they crowned him with thornes, perhaps there might be ſome <hi>Roſe</hi> trees among them, for (put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him to the moſt exquiſite tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,) it is likely they would uſe the moſt accurate and ſharpeſt prickles: Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thly he ſhed his blood <hi>in clauorum foſsione,</hi> when his hands and feet were nailed to the Croſſe. <hi>Foderunt manus &amp; pedes meos,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt,<note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 22.16.</note> in his perſon; they digged my hands and my f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et. It is recited and refuted by <hi>Sixtus Senenſ.</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">in Biblioth. Patrum lib. <hi>8</hi> pag. <hi>625.</hi>
               </note> as a Hereſie of the Iewes, that thoſe words are not to be referred to our <hi>Saviour Chriſt,</hi> and that hee was not nayled, but tyed to the Croſſe: But the print of the nayles was ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, that it<note n="z" place="margin">Iohn 20.25, 27.</note> was ſeene and felt by <hi>Thomas:</hi> and if we may beleeve <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 17.</note> the nayles he was nayled with were ſo bigge, that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> made of them a bridle and an Helmet. The
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152100:17"/>ſeaventh and laſt effuſion of his blood was <hi>in lateris apertione,</hi> when his ſide<note n="b" place="margin">Iohn 19.34.</note> was pierced with a Speare, and forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with came thereout water, and blood, ſo that the blood ran downe from his ſide which the Speare had pierced, from his hands and feet which the nayles had bored, from his head which the thornes had pricked, from his whole body which his ſorrow had melted, the fiſts buffeted, and the whips ſcourged. Well therefore might the Spouſe ſay<note n="c" place="margin">Sol. Song. 5.10</note> her beloved was white and ruddy, for hee was white with feare, and red with bloud: well might the Chriſtian Poet<note n="d" place="margin">Hovedenius.</note> ſay of him,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Cum cor ſentit amoris gladium,</l>
               <l>Cruor carnis rubricat pallium.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>When loves dart did pierce his ſide</l>
               <l>His garments crimſon red were dyed</l>
            </q>
            <p>Well might that Evangelicall <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Eſa. 63.1, 2.</note> ſay: Who is this that commeth up from <hi>Edom,</hi> with died garments from <hi>Bozrah?</hi> Wherefore art thou red
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152100:17"/>in thine apparell, and thy garments like him that treadeth in the Wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat? and well may our Princely Poet and <hi>Prophet Solomon</hi> call him the red <hi>Roſe</hi> of <hi>Sharon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In floribus duplex est gratia, coloris &amp; odoris,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iſidore:</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Originum. lib. <hi>17.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> flowers have a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble grace in their colour, and in their ſmell. And the <hi>Roſe</hi> hath the name, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in Greeke, <hi>quaſi bene olens,</hi> from the ſweet ſmell it gives, for it is ſweet to a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbe: and our Saviour Chriſt may truly be ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for he did reſemble the <hi>Roſe,</hi> both in colour and ſmell. As the rednes of the <hi>Roſe</hi> repreſents his paſſion, ſo the ſweet ſmell of the <hi>Roſe</hi> repreſents his ſweet converſation u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Earth. <hi>Lorinus</hi> hath obſerved<note n="g" place="margin">in Epiſt. ad <hi>Pet.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi> v. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> a fourefold ſweetneſſe of this <hi>Roſe:</hi> Firſt: he is <hi>dulcis in cogitatione ad meditandum,</hi> ſweet in the thought for meditation: his fruit (ſaies the ſpouſe<note n="h" place="margin">Sol. Song. 2 3</note>) is ſweet unto my taſt, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>David</hi> ſaies,<note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 119.103.</note> How ſweet are thy
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152100:18"/>wordes unto my taſt, yea ſweeter then honey unto my mouth. Secondly, he is <hi>dulcis in aure ad audiendum,</hi> ſweet in the care to heare him: for<note n="k" place="margin">Sol. Song. 2.14</note> ſweet is his voyce, and his countenance comely. Thirdly, he is <hi>dulcis in aſpectu ad viden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> he is ſweet in the eye for to be ſeen, for<note n="l" place="margin">Eccl. 11.27.</note> the light is ſweet, and a pleaſant thing it is for the eyes to behold the <hi>Sun.</hi> Fourthly, he is <hi>dulcis in opere ad exequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> ſweet in the worke to obey him, for.<note n="m" place="margin">Eccl. 23.27.</note> there is nothing ſweeter then to take heed unto the Commandements of the Lord. But his ſweet converſation did chiefly appeare when hee went about doing good both in words and workes: he preached the Goſpell to the poore, liberty to the captives, he<note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 11.5.</note> reſtored eyes to the blind, eares to the deafe, a tongue to the dumb, limbes to the lame, and life to the dead. In all which reſpects, wee may ſay of him with S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> 
               <hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">In Cantic Cantic.</note> 
               <hi>O bone Ieſu qui ſuavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cum Hominibus converſatus es, dulciter
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152100:18"/>cum illis locutus es.</hi> O bleſſed Saviour which didſt converſe with men moſt lovingly, and talke with them moſt ſweetly, herein ſhewing himſelfe to be the ſweet <hi>Roſe</hi> of <hi>Sharon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Floris Viriditas in hyeme abſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conditur, non amittitur:</hi> the greennes of the <hi>Roſe</hi> is hid for a time, but not quite loſt; it lies dead in the winter, but at the ſpring it ſprouts up againe; ſo our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Chriſt was dead, and hid for a time in the earth, but after three daies, he roſe againe, and appeared to his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples: he lay dayes, that he might be knowne to be dead; and but three daies, leſt he ſhould be thought to have been dead for ever. Chriſts lying in his grave was like our falling<note n="p" place="margin">Dr. <hi>And</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. <hi>Ser.</hi> 1.</note> into a Bed in our Chamber, where though we lie little better then dead (to ſee too) for the time, Yet in the Morning wee awake and ſtand up: or like the fall into a bed in our Garden; where though the ſeed putrifie and come to nothing,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152100:19"/>yet we looke to ſee it ſhoote forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in the Spring. Which Spring<note n="q" place="margin">Tertullian.</note> is the very reſurrection of the Yeare, and Chriſts reſurrection falleth out well with that time. There was hopes of this tree,<note n="r" place="margin">Iob. 14 7.</note> though it were cut downe that it would ſprout our againe, for the ſappe remained, and he revived. When the women came to ſeeke for Chriſt at the Sepulchre, they found the ſtone<note n="s" place="margin">Luke 24.2.</note> rolled away, and that was the thing that they deſired, for they conſulted together by the way<note n="t" place="margin">Mark 16 3.</note>, who ſhall roll away the ſtone for us.</p>
            <p>But the body they found not, and that was a ſtone to their hearts, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vier then the ſtone on the Sepulchre. Though they had ſo much courage as to be readie to die for Chriſt, they had not ſo much faith as to beleeve him, for he had told them before<note n="v" place="margin">Mat. 17.23.</note> that the third day he would riſe againe. If they had beleeved him, and the ſtone had beene removed from their hearts, as it was
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152100:19"/>from the Sepulchre, in ſtead of ſaying <hi>Sustulerunt Dominum,</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">John 20.13.</note> They have taken away the Lord, they would have ſaid, <hi>reſurrexit,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 28.6.</note> he is riſen: and indeed they contradict themſelves in ſaying ſo; for if he were their Lord, how could he be taken away? it was enough for <hi>Labans</hi> Idols to be ſtollen<note n="y" place="margin">Gen. 31.30.</note> when <hi>Ieſus</hi> appeared unto <hi>Mary,</hi> ſhe ſuppoſing him to be the Gardiner ſaid,<note n="z" place="margin">Iohn 20.15.</note> 
               <hi>Domine ſi tu,</hi> or ſir, if thou have borne him from hence tell mee. This Queſtion was well as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, <hi>Domine ſi ſustulisti,</hi> if you have taken him away? for none could take him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way but himſelfe. The <hi>Roſe</hi>-tree, though it be troden on and trampled on in the Winter, yet by the heat of the Sunne, by the heavenly influence, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other helpe it ſprings againe: ſo though they ſought to lay our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours honour in the duſt, and (even) trample on him, yet by the power of his Divinity (without other helpe) he did <hi>Erigere caput,</hi> lift up his head again.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152100:20"/>Happily the Gardiner (if it be a Garden <hi>Roſe</hi>) may remove ſome of the Earth for the <hi>Roſes</hi> ſpringing, and an Angell deſcended<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 28.2.</note> and rolled away the ſtone, for our Saviours riſing. Others did riſe before Chriſt, for <hi>Elijah</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1 Kings 17.22</note> raiſed the widowes dead ſonne of <hi>Zarephath,</hi> and <hi>Eliſha</hi> being alive raiſed the <hi>Shunamites</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">2 Kings 4 34</note> dead ſonne; and being dead his dead bones did raiſe<note n="d" place="margin">2 Kings 13.21</note> a dead man. Theſe were great miracles which theſe great Prophets did, but he that was anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 45.7.</note> with the oyle of gladnes above his fellowes, did lift up his head among the reſt, <hi>Quantum lenta ſolent inter viburn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cupreſsi,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Virgil.</note> as much as the loftieſt Cedars overtop the loweſt ſhrubs. What they did it was <hi>in nomine &amp; fide ejus,</hi> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Cyprian</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">de reſur. Chriſt. <hi>pag. 483.</hi>
               </note> in his owne name, and by his power; but he, as he layd downe his life of himſelfe<note n="h" place="margin">Iohn 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.18.</note> ſo he had power to take it up of himſelfe. They roſe to die againe, but he roſe to live for ever: for herein the reſemblance doth not hold
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152100:20"/>betweene him and the <hi>Roſe;</hi> the <hi>Roſe</hi> ſpringeth and dyeth againe the next winter, but Chriſt being rayſed<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 6.9.</note> from the dead, dyeth no more, death hath no more dominion over him. They did not conquer death, but death did at laſt conquer them, but Chriſt <hi>rediit victor a mortuis, inferni ſecum ſpolia trahens</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Ruffinus in Hym. Apoſt. inter oper. Cypriani.</note>, did riſe as a conquerour from the dead, carrying with him Trophyes of his triumph over death and Hell. And it was he onely <hi>Qui virtute propria ut victor prodiit de ſepultura,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">De Reſurrec. Chriſti.</note>, that by his owne power could riſe as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour out of the Sepulchre. Though they laid him in the earth, they could not keepe him under the earth, though they did <hi>Imponere Pelio Oſſam</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Virg. Georg. lib. <hi>1.</hi> v. <hi>181.</hi>
               </note>, lay a great ſtone upon the Sepulchre, but at the Spring of the reſurrection he roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, herein ſhewing himſelfe to be the ſpringing <hi>Roſe</hi> of <hi>Sharon;</hi> and ſo I come to the limitation of this attribute, <hi>Sharon. I am the Roſe of Sharon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:152100:21"/>
               <hi>Sharon</hi> is the name<note n="n" place="margin">Ainſworth in locum.</note> of a place or playne which was very fruitfull, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in King <hi>Davids</hi> herds of Cattell<note n="o" place="margin">1 Chron. 27.29.</note> were fed. And the Prophet ſpeaking of the flouriſhing of Chriſts Kingdome, ſaith<note n="p" place="margin">Iſay 35.2.</note> that the excellency of <hi>Carmel</hi> and <hi>Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> ſhall be given unto it. And in this ſenſe it ſhewes that Chriſt takes no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in them that are barren, but in them that are fruitfull in good workes: and alſo it ſhewes the fruitfull eſtate of the Church under Chriſt, that it is no barren <hi>Doe,</hi> but a fruitfull <hi>Hind:</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though before his coming ſhee was a barren Wilderneſſe, yet by him ſhe was as fruitfull as <hi>Sharon.</hi> But the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Sharon</hi> in the originall ſignifies<note n="q" place="margin">Pagnin Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> a Field in generall, as well as the Field <hi>Sharon</hi> in particular; and therefore give me leave to follow the old Tranſlation of this word, which renders it, <hi>I am the Roſe of the Field;</hi> for therein lyes hid three myſteries.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he is the <hi>Roſe</hi> of the Field, not
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152100:21"/>of the Garden: <hi>Campus enim ſine omni bumano floret adminiculo, non ſeminatus ab aliquo, non defoſſus ſarculo, non impingua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus fimo: ſic omnino, ſic virginis alvus floruit, ſic inviolata, integra, &amp; casta Mariae viſcera, tanquam paſcua aeterni vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roris, florem protulere, cujus pulchritudo non viderit corruptionem, cujus gloria in perpetuum non marceſcat,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">De Adventu. Ser. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> The Field flouriſheth without mans induſtry, it is neither ſowed nor digged nor dunged by man, but the Flowers grow in it by the providence of God: ſo Chriſt was conceived by the holy Ghoſt without the help of man, the virgins Wombe did flouriſh, and her chaſte bowels (like a Field of eternall greenneſſe) brought forth a Flower whoſe beauty never ſaw corruption, and whoſe glory ſhal never wither. The flowers of the Feild<note n="ſ" place="margin">Doctor <hi>Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liams</hi> 7 Gold Candleſt tract of the Incarn.</note> have onely a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Heaven, that is, the Sunne by whoſe heat and vertue they grow, and a mother in earth, that is, the ground
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152100:22"/>from whence they ſpring: ſo this Flower of the root of <hi>Ieſſe</hi> had onely a father in Heaven, God: and a mother in earth, the virgin. He was <hi>Deus de pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, homo de matre, de patris immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, de matris virginitate, de patre ſine matre, de matre ſine patre, de patre ſine tempore, de matre ſine ſemine,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">De Tempore Ser <hi>23.</hi>
               </note>, he was God of his father, man of his mother, of the immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his father, of the virginity of his mother, of his father without a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of his mother without a father, of his father without time, of his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without ſeed. <hi>Anſelmus</hi> hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved<note n="v" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 8.</note> foure waies by which man may come into the world. Firſt, by the help of man and woman, the common way. Secondly, without the help both of man and woman; as <hi>Adam.</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of a man without a woman, as <hi>Eve.</hi> Fourthly, of a woman without a man, as Chriſt. God made the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> without the help of man,<note n="w" place="margin">Gen. 2.7.</note> for God
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152100:22"/>formed him of the duſt of the ground, and breathed into his noſtrills the breath of life; ſo God made the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> without the help of man, but the holy Ghoſt overſhadowed the virgin, and ſhe conceived. <hi>Ergo ſi tunc licuit hominem ſine homine naſci, cur non licuit hominem ſine homine de Maria virgine procreari,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Austin</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">De Tempore Ser. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note>, If man might then bee made without mans helpe, why ſhould not the man Chriſt Ieſus be borne of a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin without the help of man? Divers have rendred divers reaſons why it ſhould be ſo, firſt, becauſe as that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was a virgin by whom ſinne was ſpread among men, (as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap</hi> 33.</note> that <hi>Eve</hi> was a virgin when ſhee gave her husband of the forbidden fruit) ſo was it fit that ſhe ſhould be a virgin, by whom a Saviour ſhould be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced for man: for it pleaſed God that the fall and riſing f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om ſinne, the ſalve and the ſore ſhould be brought unto us the ſame<note n="z" place="margin">Ludolph de vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a Chri pan. 1. cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> way, though not by the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152100:23"/>ſame meanes: <hi>Ceciderat autem homo dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolo deſtinante, ſerpente exequente, dialogo interveniente, &amp; muliere conſentiente</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Beda apud Ludolph.</note>, When man, fell the divell appoynted the Serpent obeyed, the ſpeech paſſed betweene the woman and the Serpent, and ſhee conſented. Contrarily when man was reſtored; <hi>Deo destinante, Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo exequente, dialogo interveniente, &amp; vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine conſentiente,</hi> God appoynted, the Angell obeyed, the ſpeech concurred, and the virgin conſented. Secondly, Chriſts generation was a figure of our Regeneration, and it was fit, ſaith Saint <hi>August.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">De Sanctis Ser. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> that Chriſt the head ſhould be borne of a virgin, to ſignify that his members (the children of God) muſt be borne of a virgin the Church: ſo the Apoſtle tells the <hi>Corinthians</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">2 Cor. 11.2.</note>, I have eſpouſed you to one husband, that I may preſent you as a chaſte virgin unto Chriſt: for Chriſts Church (like his mother) is both a mother and a mayd, a mother (being betrothed to him)
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152100:23"/>as ſhe brings forth, and brings up ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny children for him, and a virgin as ſhe remaynes ſpotles before him. Thirdly, being God,<note n="d" place="margin">Barrad To. <hi>1.</hi> lib. <hi>7</hi> cap <hi>10.</hi>
               </note>, it was fit that he ſhould be borne of none elſe but a virgin: and it was fit that a virgin ſhould bring forth none but God. Fourthly, Chriſt had a father in Heaven before, God was his Father by an ineffable generation, and therefore he was not to have a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on earth, leſt he ſhould have had two fathers. Fifthly, the truth was to anſwer to the tipe; <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> was a type of Chriſt, and it is ſaid of him,<note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 7.3.</note> that hee was without father, without mother; ſo Chriſt was God without mother, and man without father. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Chriſt<note n="f" place="margin">Stap. Promp. Mor. In ſeſt. Annunc.</note> was to take away ſinne, which he could not have done if hee himſelfe had been borne in ſinne; and he could not have been free from ſinne, had he not been borne of a virgin: our Saviour himſelfe tells us<note n="g" place="margin">John 3.6.</note>, that which is borne of the fleſh is fleſh. All men
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152100:24"/>that are begotten of men may ſay with the Prophet <hi>David</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 51.5.</note>, Behold I was ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in iniquity, and in ſinne did my mother conceive me. Hee onely was free from originall corruption, that came not into the World by an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary conception. This was figured by many things in the old Teſtament, by the gate of the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> which was ſhut, and the Lord ſaid<note n="i" place="margin">Ezek. 44.1, 2.</note> it ſhall be ſhut, it ſhall not bee opened, and no man ſhall enter in by it, becauſe the Lord the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> hath entred in by it: by <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple that was built<note n="k" place="margin">1. Kings 6.7</note> without an iron inſtrument: by the ſtone<note n="l" place="margin">Dan. 2 45.</note> cut out of the Mountaine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hands; and <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod that<note n="m" place="margin">Numb. 17.7.</note> bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomed and brought forth ripe Almonds without ſeed, ſignifyed that CHRIST ſhould bee brought forth of a virgin without mans ſeed, or hands, or helpe. <hi>Sicut non poterat caro niſi de carne naſci, it a non poterat Dei caro de foemineo utero niſi ſine generante prodire,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">De Tempor. Ser. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:152100:24"/>As fleſh could not bee borne without fleſh, ſo the ſonne of God could not be borne but without carnall generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. He came not into the world by the helpe of man, but by, the providence, of God here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in reſembling the <hi>roſe</hi> of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon field.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>the Roſe of the Field</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Doctor</hi> Dove in loc.</note> is not incloſed, and made private to a few, as the garden <hi>Roſe</hi> is, but is common to all that will gather it: So Chriſt is not incloſed to a few, but is common to all that will lay hold upon him. Once (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed) before Chriſts comming, Chriſt might properly have been ſaid to bee <hi>the Roſe of Sharon,</hi> when the Iewes were Gods peculiar people. Then in <hi>Iuda</hi> p was God knowne,<note place="margin">Pſal. 76.1.</note> and his name was great in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> God did then chooſe for himſelfe one Vine of all the Trees of the Forreſt, one <hi>Roſe</hi> of all the Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Field, one <hi>Dove</hi> of all the Birds of the ayre, and one Nation of all the Kingdomes of the World: but ſince his manifeſtation in the fleſh, the vayle
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152100:25"/>of the Temple was rent<note n="q" place="margin">Luke 23 45.</note>, and the middle wall of partition was broken downe<note n="r" place="margin">Eph. 2.14.</note>, and he became <hi>the Roſe of the Field.</hi> And although the Apoſtles at the firſt were commanded<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mat. 10.5.</note> not to goe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the way of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> nor to enter into any City of the <hi>Samaritanes,</hi> yet afterwards their commiſſion was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, and they were commanded<note n="t" place="margin">Mark. 16.15.</note> to preach the Goſpell through the World. It is well obſerved<note n="v" place="margin">Doctor <hi>Boys</hi> on the Epiſt. 2. Sunday after <hi>Eaſter.</hi>
               </note> that GOD com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>Moſes</hi> to put in his perfume<note n="w" place="margin">Exod. 30 34.</note> as much <hi>Galbanum</hi> as <hi>Frankincenſe,</hi> and as much <hi>Frankincenſe</hi> as <hi>Galbanum,</hi> to ſignify that Chriſt in his oblation on the croſſe, a ſacrifice<note n="x" place="margin">Epheſ. 5.2.</note> of a ſweet ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſavour unto God, ſhed as much bloud for the labouring man that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the Plow, as for the Prince that ſitteth on the Throne: and that his precious bloud hath, greater force in ſome then in other, is not the fault of him that did ſo well impart it, but of them which do ſo ill imploy it. Chriſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152100:25"/>was borne in a common <hi>Inne, diverſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium dicitur, quia ibi diverſi conveniunt,</hi> ſaith Iſidore<note n="y" place="margin">Apud Gorran.</note> he receives (like that) all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mers. <hi>In medio Templi miſericordia eſt, non in angulo aut diverſorio: In communi poſita est, offertur omnibus, &amp; nemo illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us expers niſi qui renuit,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard.</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">In Purifi. pag. 101.</note> The mercy of God was placed in the midſt of the Temple, not in ſome nooke or corner, it is proffered to all, and none goes without it, but he that refuſeth it: for though the <hi>Roſe</hi> of the Field lyeth common to all, yet are not all partakers of the benefit of it, but onely theſe that uſe it for ſmell or for medicine: ſo although Chriſts merits are common to all, hee keepes open houſe for all commers, yet thoſe onely have full benefit by them that lay hold upon them. God loved the World (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed)<note n="a" place="margin">John 3.16</note> when he gave his onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Sonne (not onely to it, but for it) but thoſe onely that believe on him ſhall not periſh, but have life everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152100:26"/>
               <hi>Praedicatio Chriſti neminem excludit niſi qui ſeſe ſuapte excluſerit perfidia</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Bullinger in Tit. <hi>2 11.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>Christ</hi> excludes none but thoſe that exclude themſelves by unbeliefe. The Apoſtle tells us<note n="c" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.15.</note> that <hi>Christ</hi> dyed for all: And God<note n="d" place="margin">1 Tim 2.4.</note> will have all men to bee ſaved, not all of the World, as <hi>Origen.</hi> would have it<note n="e" place="margin">Hom <hi>9</hi> in Gen &amp; recenſetur in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter errores ejus ab Abra. Scul. teto in medull. Patr. To. <hi>1.</hi> lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note>, that all men and divells alſo ſhall be ſaved at the laſt day. But ſome ſay, God will have all men to be ſaved which are ſaved, not that there is none that ſhall not be ſaved, but that all thoſe that are ſaved, are ſaved by the good will and pleaſure of God, ſo <hi>Aquinas</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Part.</hi> 1. <hi>Quaeſt</hi> 19. <hi>Art.</hi> 6.</note>. or as others, God will <hi>voluntate qua invitat,</hi> Becauſe he puts no blocke in the way, <hi>non voluntate qua efficit,</hi> for he doth not remove the impediment: ſo a learned profeſſor<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Doctor</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux Lect. Oxon Lec. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> of Theology or: elſe God will <hi>voluntate antecedente, non conſequente,</hi> with his antecedent, not conſequent will; ſo <hi>Aquinas</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi prins.</note> from <hi>Damaſcen:</hi> as the Iudge in his antecedent will would have all men to live, but in his conſequent will
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152100:26"/>he would have the malefactors to be put to death; ſo God <hi>(antecedenter)</hi> will have all men to be ſaved, but <hi>(con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uenter)</hi> hee will have the wicked damned. Or elſe Chriſt dyed for all <hi>ſecundum ſufficientiam,</hi> in reſpect of the ſufficiency thereof, but not <hi>ſecundum efficientiam,</hi> in regard of the efficiency thereof, as being effectuall onely to the faithfull or elect of God, ſo the Maſter of the Sentences<note n="i" place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> diſtin. <hi>19.</hi> &amp; Nich. de Orbell. com. in Sent.</note>; though that diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction be exploded by many as well of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which hold that onely to bee ſufficient which is effectuall. <hi>Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liricus</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">De Trop. &amp; Schem. Sacr. Litt. Trac. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> ſaies, <hi>Christus actu paſſus eſt pro omnibus ſed non actu ſalvantur, aut omnibus actuejus paſſio prodest,</hi> Chriſt ſuffered effectnally for all, but his ſufferings are not effectuall unto all: others would have the word (all) to bee underſtood, <hi>non de ſingulis generum, ſed de generibus ſingulorum,</hi> and then it is taken <hi>distributive,</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:152100:27"/>not Collective, as Logicians ſpeake<note n="l" place="margin">Ariſt. <hi>2.</hi> Pol. cap <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>, diſtributively for all ſorts and conditions of men, high and low, rich and poore <hi>Iew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> not univerſally for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very particular perſon, ſo S. <hi>Augustine,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">De Correp. &amp; Gra. &amp; Coſma. in <hi>1.</hi> Tim.</note> Laſtly, ſuppoſe it bee underſtood <hi>de individuis omnibus</hi> (as ſome)<note n="n" place="margin">Arctius in <hi>1</hi> ad Tim cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> of all particular perſons, God will have all to be ſaved <hi>(conditionaliter)</hi> if they will uſe and apply the meanes. Chriſts bloud is like the poole of <hi>Betheſda</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">John. 5.4.</note>, which was able to cure all manner of diſeaſes, but it cured none but thoſe that did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into it. So though it be true which ſome<note n="p" place="margin">Clem. <hi>5.</hi> apud Barradium.</note> affirme, <hi>unam guttam ſanguinis Chriſti pro redemptione totius humani ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris ſuffeciſſe,</hi> That one drop of Chriſts bloud was of ſufficient vertue for the redemption of all mankind, yet (though it were all ſhed) it is of no more vertue to him that will not lay hold upon it, then a pardon would bee benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to him that ſhould either refuſe or rend it. The leaſt drop of Chriſts bloud
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152100:27"/>(as hath been ſaid) in reſpect of the excellency of the perſon, the innocency of the nature, and the efficacy of the <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe,</hi> was ſufficient to redeeme the World, yet this excellent ſalve ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne for all ſores, doth no more good to many, then the moſt ſoveraigne <hi>Roſe</hi> or <hi>Hearb</hi> of the Field can worke them health that will not apply it to their ſeverall diſeaſes. <hi>Si quis non credit in Chriſtum, generali beneficio ipſe ſe frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat, ut ſi quis clauſis fenestris radios ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis excludat</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Ser. 8. in Pſ. 118.</note> If any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve not in Chriſt hee deprives him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of the benefit of his paſſion, as if one by ſhutting the windowes ſhould ſhut out the light of the Sun: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he that will not gather this <hi>Roſe,</hi> let him blame himſelfe, ſeeing hee is not incloſed in the garden, but the <hi>Roſe</hi> of the open Field.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the <hi>Roſe of the Field</hi> is for profit as well as pleaſure, it being health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for many Medicines, as the <hi>Herba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:152100:28"/>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Dodanaeus Lantgraoe.</note> have obſerved: ſo <hi>Christ</hi> was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for us, and healthfull unto us. He was knowne in the old Teſtament by this name, I am<note n="ſ" place="margin">Exod 3.14.</note>, leaving a blanke for us to write what we will, and he will ſupply the reſt. I am your Saviour, your Phyſitian, your guide, your gayne, your all in all, for ſo he is to them that love him. Before Chriſts coming the whole World was weake and wicked, ſickly and ſinfull. The generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of goodnes, the Dropſie of covetouſnes, the Tympany of pride, the Gout of idlenes, the tertian of incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency, and the quotidian of Glutto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny did ſhew that <hi>Adam</hi> was turned <hi>Enoſh,</hi> full of infirmity. Neither had this infirmity ſeiſed partially on it, but with <hi>Iob</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Job. 2.7.</note> from the ſole of the foot to the crowne of the head, they are all<note n="v" place="margin">Pſal. 14.1.</note> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt. <hi>Nulla ſanctitas, nulla ſanitas.</hi> Nor was this malady but newly entred, or continued onely twelve yeares, as the<note n="w" place="margin">Lu. 8 43.</note> iſſue of bloud had with the woman,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152100:28"/>or thirty and eight yeeres, as the mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity<note n="x" place="margin">John 5.5.</note> at the poole of <hi>Betheſdah,</hi> but the World had lyen bedrid almoſt foure thouſand yeeres, given quite over by the Law unto death; in this forlorne hope came the<note n="y" place="margin">John 11.25.</note> reſurrection &amp; the life, the ſole <hi>Saviour</hi> and great phyſitian of the world, crying out for our comfort, the world is not dead, but ſleepeth; reſtoring health two wayes, mediate, and immediate. Firſt, mediate, by meanes: not as once, by clay and ſpittle. Secondly,<note n="z" place="margin">John 9.6.</note> as he reſtored ſight to the blind: or as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> to <hi>Hezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ab</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">2 Kings 20.7.</note>, by a lump of dry <hi>Figgs,</hi> nor as <hi>Eliſha</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">2 Kings 5.10</note> to <hi>Naaman,</hi> by the waters of <hi>Iordan:</hi> but a <hi>Samaritanes</hi> cure<note n="c" place="margin">Luke 10.34</note>, Wine to ſearch, and Oyle to ſupple, the Law being a corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to kill the dead fleſh, and the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pella Cordiall to comfort the heart. And this phyſick doth hee ſtill admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter by his inſtruments, his Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors: by them that plant in the Pulpit, and water in the preſſe, that plant in their Doctrine, and water in their
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152100:29"/>converſation: by them that admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſuch phyſick as he doth direct and apply ſuch ſalves as the word doth preſcribe for the healing of ſick ſoules Secondly, Chriſt heals immediately b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> himſelfe; pride was <hi>Adams</hi> bane, Chriſt cured it by humility; man (ſurfeting) fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> by the forbidden Tree, Chriſt (faſting cured it by the curſed Tree. Other Phy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitians<note n="d" place="margin">Stella in Luc. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> reſtore health by opening o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>veynes, by letting of bloud, by giving o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Potions, and by preſcribing of dyet, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt (this heavenly Phyſitian) made himſelfe the Phyſick to heale us,<note n="e" place="margin">Staplet. Prom. mor. Dom. inf. oct. nat. Dom</note> he took the bitter Potion<note n="f" place="margin">John 19.29</note> of vineger, the deit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> faſting<note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 4 2.</note>, the bloud-letting in his Hands his Feete, his Side, his Head his Body <hi>Mirabile plane &amp; incomparabile genus me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicinae, propter quam medicus voluit aegrote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re, &amp; aegrotos ipſos, quibus ſalutis remediu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> procuravit, ſua decrevit infirmitate curan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſaith S. <hi>Aust.</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">De Sanctis Ser. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> It was a wonderfull an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> incomparable kind of phyſick for which the Phyſitian would bee ſick, and dete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mine
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152100:29"/>to cure thoſe ſick perſons (to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he procures health) by his owne infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. <hi>Eſſe hominis filius voluit ut nos Dei fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> faceret, humiliavit ſe ut populum qui pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> jacebat erigeret, vnlneratus est, ut vulne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra nostra ſanaret, ſervivit ut ad libertatem ſervientes extraheret, mori ſuſtinuit ut im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitatem mortalibus exhiberet</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Cyprian</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">De opere &amp; Elemoſ pag. <hi>3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4</hi>
               </note>. He would be made the ſon of man to make us the Sonnes of God, he bumbled himſelfe that hee might exalt the humble, he was wounded that hee might heale our wounds, he became a ſervant that he might ſet us at liberty that were ſervants, he dyed to reſtore immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality to mortall men. And indeed <hi>Chriſts</hi> whole life, whether you conſider his Doctrine or his doings, was healthfull and medicinable to us, if we obey his precepts, or imitate his patterne.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Text</hi> hath been hitherto as a fruitfull Field wherein I have gathered ſome corne, I ſhall now bind ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of it up in ſheaves that you may the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152100:30"/>better carry it away with you. Firſt, therefore, here we may ſee Chriſts love to us with aſtoniſhment and admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. What the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſaid concerning <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">John. 11.36.</note> (when Chriſt rayſed him from dead) behold how he loved him; ſo may we ſay, behold how he loved us, how deare and pretious our life hath been in his eyes may appeare by the greatnes of the price which hee payd for it, even his owne life. <hi>Quam indebita miſeratio, quam grata dilectio, &amp;c. regem gloriae cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figi pro deſpicatiſsimo vermiculo</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Div. Bern.</note>! O how undeſerved is that mercy, how free is that love, that the King of glory ſhould be crucifyed for deſpicable Wormes! It was a great love<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cowper. on</hi> Rom. 8.</note> that <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhewed to <hi>Lot,</hi> in hazarding his owne life<note n="n" place="margin">Gen. 14.14</note>, and the lives of his family to reſcue him out of the hands of <hi>Chedorlaomer;</hi> but not comparable that love which our kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, the Lord Ieſus, hath ſhewed unto us, who hath given his life to deliver us out of the hand of our enemyes. It was a wonderfull great love that God
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152100:30"/>would make man like himſelfe, and all things for man, greater love; that he himſelfe would be made man; but great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of all that he would dy for his ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Secondly, let us conſider the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſnes of ſinne with hatred and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation. Thouſands of Rams<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Micah.</hi> 67.</note>, nor ten thouſands of Rivers of Oyle, could not make ſatiſfaction for ſinne, neither could the fruit of our body make ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for the ſinne of our ſoule, but the Son of God muſt needs dy for the ſins of man. If ſinne coſt Chriſt ſo deare, doubtles it will coſt us dearer, except we repent. <hi>Memoria ergo crucifixi in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis crucifigat omne peccatum</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Div. Bern.</note>, is an excellent counſaile, and worthy our practice: therefore let the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of Chriſt crucified cauſe us to crucify all ſin in us, he ſtretched out his hands on the Croſſe to embrace us, and let not us ſtretch out our hands to wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ednes to diſgrace him, he was crucifyed for us, let not us crucify him againe by
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152100:31"/>our ſins, but crucify our ſins that cauſed him to be crucified. Thirdly, Chriſt is a patterne for our imitation, and that in three things. Firſt, we muſt imitate him in the ſweetnes of our action, eſpecially in dong good. Secondly, in our reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, which is twofold, the firſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the other is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The one is a reſurrection of the dead, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is a reſurrection from the dead: We muſt riſe from the death of ſinne to the life of grace, if wee meane to riſe from the death of the grave unto the life of glory. But we muſt not riſe as the <hi>Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree</hi> doth at the ſpring to dy againe the next winter, but with Chriſt, he being rayſed from the dead<note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 6 9.</note> dyeth no more, death hath no more dominion over him, and we muſt ſo riſe from the death of ſin, that we never commit the ſame ſins againe. Thirdly, as Chriſt was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and borne for us, ſo muſt we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and beare him in our hearts. There is a threefold nativity of Chriſt, Divine
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152100:31"/>from his Father, fleſhly from his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſpirituall in the mind. <hi>Ex patre naſcitur ſemper, de matre natus eſt ſemel, in mente naſcitur ſaepe,</hi> ſaith <hi>Innocentius</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Ser. <hi>3.</hi> apud Barrad.</note>; He is borne of his father alwayes, he was borne of his Mother once, and is borne in the mind often, and we muſt endev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to keepe him there alwayes. Forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, here is alſo matter of conſolation, and that in a double reſpect, firſt as <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>Roſe</hi> of the common Field, and lyes open to all, he refuſeth none but thoſe that refuſe him. Secondly, becauſe he is the Phyſitian of our Soules, that is able to cure them, hiding allour ſins, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling all our Sores, giving us ſpirituall health here, and eternall health and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines hereafter. Laſtly, as <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſaid to his ſervant concerning the good <hi>Shuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">2 Kings. 4.13.</note>: She hath been carefull for us with all this care, what is to be done for her? ſo may I ſay to you concerning our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, he hath been thus carefull for us, what ſhall we doe againe for him? As
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152100:32"/>he dranke to us in the cup of ſalvation, ſo let us pledge him in the cup of thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving: as he gave himſelfe a propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory ſacrifice for us, ſo let us give up our ſelves a gratulatory ſacrifice of prayſe and thankeſgiving to him. And let us fall downe with the<note n="t" place="margin">Revel. 19 4.</note> foure and twenty el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and the fowre beaſts, prayſing GOD with our Church, and ſaying.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Glory be to God on high, and in earth peace, good will toward men. We prayſe thee, wee bleſſe thee, we worſhip thee, we glorify thee, we give thankes unto thee O, Lord God, heavenly King, for all thy bleſſings bestowed upon us, for that thou hast ſent thy Sonne Ieſus Chriſt not only to live among men, but to dy for men: Grant (O Lord) that we may all be partakers of all the benefits of his paſsion. And that for the ſame Ieſus Christ his ſake, who as he died for ſin, ſo he ever lives to make interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for ſinnes. To whom with thee, and the Holy Spirit, be all honour, and glory, now and for ever,</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:152100:32"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable, FERDINAND O, <hi>Lord</hi> HASTINGS, <hi>my very good Lord.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HAT <hi>Thucidides</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes, experience proves true, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is not lyable to any account, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, whatſoever a man ſpeakes (but eſpecially writes) it layes him open to others cenſure, unto which I have now expoſed my ſelfe, and crave your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection. Your <hi>Honour</hi> muſt not expect any high straynes in this Sermon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:152100:33"/>
               <hi>Haud facile emergunt quorum virtutibus obſtat Res anguſta domi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As it is I deſire your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips</hi> acceptance of it, as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of ſome part of that duty and ſervice I owe your <hi>Honor.</hi> The God of mercie poure downe his mercies on your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> your Honourable <hi>Lady,</hi> and hopefull children. Which ſhall alwaies be the praier of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips in all duty, and ſervice. WILLIAM PARKS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="lecture">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152100:33"/>
            <head>THE ROSE AND LILY.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>SOLOMONS SONG. 2.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I am the <hi>Roſe</hi> of Sharon, and the <hi>Lily</hi> of the vallyes.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat the Queene of <hi>Shebah</hi> told <hi>Solomon,</hi> that<note n="a" place="margin">1 Kings 10.6, 7.</note> though it were a true report which ſhee had heard of him, yet the one halfe was not told her: ſo may I ſay unto you concerning this <hi>Text,</hi> though it bee a true report you have heard of him that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152100:34"/>is greater then <hi>Solomon</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 12.42.</note>; yet the one halfe is not told you. For this <hi>Text</hi> is a moſt fertile and fruitfull Field, contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning variety of no leſſe profitable then pleaſant Flowers, from whence I have already brought you a Poſy made of <hi>Roſes,</hi> and now give me leave from the ſame Garden to preſent unto you a Poſy compoſed of <hi>Liles.</hi> The <hi>Lily</hi> is next in nobility to the <hi>Roſe,</hi> ſaith <hi>Pliny</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 2 <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note>, and therefore as I have ſhewed you wherein Chriſt reſembles the <hi>Roſe,</hi> ſo muſt I now ſhew you how hee is the <hi>Lily of the vallyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The writers<note n="d" place="margin">Ariſt. Pliny Dodan.</note> of the nature of things have written much in the commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the <hi>Lily,</hi> affirming it to bee a moſt fine Flower, both for fragrant ſmell and curious colours. And many Princes did beare it in their creſts and Eſcutchions, but I leave this for <hi>Heralds</hi> to diſcourſe of, and for <hi>Herbaliſts</hi> to diſcuſſe, and ſhall onely ſhew you that Chriſt reſembles the <hi>Lily</hi> in theſe fowre
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152100:34"/>reſpects. Firſt, the Flower of the <hi>Lily</hi> is lifted upward, and open toward Heaven, but toward the earth it is cloſe and ſhut; ſo Chriſt had his mind open toward Heaven, ſet on heavenly things, but he alwayes neglected and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned earthly things. Secondly, the leaves of the <hi>Lily</hi> ſpread outward, and bend downward; ſo Chriſt extended his benefits downward, even to his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Thirdly, the whiteneſſe of the <hi>Lily</hi> may ſignify Chriſts eternity, or his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ocency. Fourthly, the <hi>Lily</hi> growes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thornes, and Chriſt (when hee was upon the Earth) was converſant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mong ſinners: in theſe reſpects hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hewed himſelfe to bee the <hi>Lily of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ally<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</hi> And firſt of the firſt, the Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>Lily</hi> is open toward Heaven, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it cloſe toward the earth, ſo Chriſt had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s affections open toward heavenly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ings, but he neglected earthly.</p>
            <p>As Chriſt was ſometime<note n="e" place="margin">Luke 2.51.</note> ſubject to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s Mother, ſo was he alwayes obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152100:35"/>to his father. He that<note n="f" place="margin">John 3.31.</note> came from above, did ſet his affections on thing above.<note n="g" place="margin">Coloſ. 3, 2.</note> This <hi>Lily</hi> had alwayes the ey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of his affections open toward heave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (it being his chiefeſt care to doe his he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>venly fathers<note n="h" place="margin">Luke 2.49.</note> buſines) but cloſe ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> toward earth and earthly things. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are three<note n="i" place="margin">Ludo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ph de vita Chriſti. part <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>67.</hi>
               </note> things that hinder us fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> having the eyes of our ſoules open t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward Heaven, but Chriſt was free fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them all. Firſt, <hi>quando oculus nimis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cupatur circa ſenſibilia,</hi> when the eye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> too much imployed about ſenſible o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>jects, namely when the affection is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> on earthly things, for then is the eye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſoule dazled with the duſt of co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>touſnes, but Chriſt had no mind <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> earthly riches, but as hee had none, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he did deſire none. Secondly, <hi>quando <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mis occupatur circa delectabilia,</hi> when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is too much taken up with delight<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> things, the carnall deſires of the fleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for then the eye is blinded with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fire of concupiſcence: but Chriſt w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:152100:35"/>free from that, and it is ſuch a ſinne that the divell himſelfe would not tempt Chriſt by that, though hee tempted him by riches and the glory of the World<note n="k" place="margin">Mat. 4</note> Thirdly, <hi>quando nimis occupatur circa ſublimia,</hi> when it is intent on lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty things, namely ambitiouſly taken up with the pompe and glory of the World, for then the eye is darkned with the ſmoake of pride, but Chriſt was free from that, for he<note n="l" place="margin">John. 6.16.</note> fled from thoſe that would have made him King. So that he had no worldly riches to clog him, no carnall pleaſures to allure him, no ambitious thoughts to ſtop him, nor any of thoſe to hinder him for having his eyes and thoughts ſettled on heavenly things. Hee was not like the <hi>Baſiliskes</hi> which <hi>Pliny</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 8.</note> calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they looke downward, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not turne their countenance upward toward the Firmament: but rather he was like the fiſh which <hi>Albertus</hi> (as I remember) makes mention of, that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152100:36"/>had but one eye, placed in his pole, ſo that he alwayes looked upward, mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things above, but hee did altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neglect (if not contemne) all earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things. Which will the better ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare if we conſider his poverty in his birth, in his life, and in his death. Firſt, in his birth: <hi>Exigua magni pompa puer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perii,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Cyprian</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Serm. de na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti. Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſti.</note>, There was but ſmall pomp at this great birth; he was borne in ſo meane a manner; that the cratch was his cradle, the<note n="o" place="margin">Luke 2.7.</note> manger his chamber, and the ſtable his Inne. If the Sun of God will needs come and dwell among the ſons of men, Kings palaces (me thinks) were bad enough to receive ſo worthy a perſon, and yet (behold) the ſtatelieſt place for his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment is a ſtable. If the King of Heaven will needs come into the earth, the moſt princely chamber were fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt for him to be lodged in, and yet (behold) he lies in a manger. If King <hi>Solomon</hi> was ſo raviſhed with admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152100:36"/>when hee conſidered that GOD would reſide at the Temple in <hi>Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> (which was ſo glorious that it was<note n="p" place="margin">1 Kings 6.38.</note> ſeaven yeares, in building) that hee cries out<note n="q" place="margin">1 Kings 8.27</note>, But will GOD indeed dwell on the earth? behold the Heaven, and the Heaven of heavens cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne thee, how much leſſe the houſe that I have made? how much more would he have admired, had he come into this ſtable, and found Chriſt (this Lord of life) lying in a manger? Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, in his life-time he was poorer then the beaſts of the Field, and the Birds of the Ayre, for they have dens and neſts to rooſt and to reſt in, but hee had not a place where to lay his head, as himſelfe reſtifies<note n="r" place="margin">Mat. 8.20.</note>. And as for his outward eſtate he was ſo poore, that when tribute was demanded of him, he had nothing to pay it, but he ſends <hi>Peter</hi> with an angle<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mat. 17.27.</note> to catch a fiſh to bring him money to pay it: therein ſhewing great<note n="t" place="margin">Ianſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. conc. cap. <hi>69</hi>
               </note> Majeſty as well as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152100:37"/>poverty, his poverty in that he had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wherewith to pay it, and his Majeſty in that being Lord of Sea as well as Land, he commands a Fiſh to do it for him. So that as the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes of himſelfe,<note n="u" place="margin">2 Cor. 6.10.</note> he was as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nothing, and yet poſſeſſing all things; ſo may I ſay of Chriſt, he poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed nothing, and yet he was Lord of all. When <hi>Eriene.</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">Cicero Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> the City where <hi>Byas</hi> dwelt was taken by the enemies, and the Citizens fled, carying as much of their ſubſtance with them as they could, when he was admoniſhed by ſome to doe the like, <hi>Ego quidem (inquit) fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio, nam omnia mea mecum porto;</hi> I doe it (ſaid he) already, for I alwayes car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry all my goods about me: ſo lightly did he eſteeme of thoſe <hi>ludibria fortunae,</hi> (riches) that he thought them not worth a carrying: ſo Chriſt carryed all his goods about him, ſo that when he died, he needed no executors to prove his will, for<note n="x" place="margin">John 19 23.</note> the Souldiers parted his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152100:37"/>goods among them, and hee had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for them to part, but onely his garments.<note place="margin">Mat. 27.35.</note> I have heared a ſtory of <hi>Richard Nevile,</hi> ſometime Earle of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> (how true it is, I know not) that when the people would have made him King, hee refuſed that dignity, ſaying, that he had rather make Kings then be one: but this I know, he that<note n="y" place="margin">Pſal. 85.7</note> putteth downe one, and ſetteth up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, when the people would have made him King, refuſed it. <hi>Erat Rex qui timebat fieri Rex: nec talis Rex qui ab hominibus fieret, ſed talis qui homini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus regnum daret,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Augustine</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">In John <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ract. 23.</note> He was a King that feared to bee made a King, not ſuch a King that ſhould be made by men, but ſuch a King as ſhould give a Kingdome to men. A King hee was indeed, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to bee ſo<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 2.2.</note> by the wiſe men at his birth. <hi>Nathanel</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">John 1.44.</note>, and the whole multitude acknowledged him<note n="c" place="margin">Luke 19.38.</note> to bee King in his Life: at his
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152100:38"/>death <hi>Pilate</hi> wrote him King of the <hi>Iewes</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">John 19, 19.22.</note>, and would not alter that title, and yet hee would not be made a King by the people, leſt<note n="e" place="margin">Calvin in Iohn <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> his ſpirituall King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhould have been at an end; he refuſed to be made a King on earth, for hee was already King of Heaven and earth. Thirdly at his death he was ſo poore, that he had neither Sepulchre nor winding ſheet of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s owne, but<note n="f" place="margin">John 19.38.39.</note> 
               <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Nicodemus</hi> were faine to ſupply them. Even the richeſt men and moſt puiſſant Monarchs have nothing at their deathes, that they may proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call their owne, but onely their Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchres. We may ſay of them all as S. <hi>Austin</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Ad fra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. in Er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o. Ser. <hi>48.</hi>
               </note> ſpeakes of <hi>Caeſars</hi> Tombe; Though hee were the feare of men, and terror of Princes, yet all his great riches, his titles of Honour and Dignity, his Crowne and Scepter, Speare and Sword, <hi>Omnia ſibi pariter defecerunt, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do defecit ſpiritus ejus: &amp; reliquerunt eum captivatum in ſepulchro trium brachi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152100:38"/>plenum foetore &amp; putredine.</hi> All thoſe things left him (as they doe all men elſe) when he was bereft of his ſoule, and left him nothing but a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre of ſix cubits to conteyne him; but Chriſt, as he was without all earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pompe in his life, ſo at his death he had not ſo much as a Sepulchre or winding ſheer of his owne, untill they were given him. In all which reſpects we may ſay of him with S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">De Cat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>z. r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dibus.</note>, <hi>Omnia bona terrena contempſit homo Christ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, ut nobis ea contemnenda monstraret.</hi> The man Chriſt Ieſus did contemne all earthly things, to teach us alſo to doe the like. It was a curſe layd upon the Serpent in Paradiſe<note n="i" place="margin">Gen. 3.14.</note>, upon thy belly ſhalt thou goe, and duſt ſhalt thou eat all the dayes of thy life, and therefore the ſeed of the woman<note n="k" place="margin">Ver. 15.</note> being to break the head of the Serpent, went not on his belly, nor had his affections pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced on the earth, but was lifted <hi>ſurſum verſus coelum,</hi> upward toward Heaven,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152100:39"/>therein reſembling the Flower of the <hi>Lily of the Valleys.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>folia liliorum non ſolum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latantur ad latera, ſed etiam inferius de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinant ad ima,</hi> the Leaves of the <hi>Lily</hi> do not onely extend outward, but bend downward, ſo Chriſt extended his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits farr off, and even to his enemies. The Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> tells the <hi>Gentiles</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Eph. 2 13.</note>, that now in Chriſt Ieſus yee who ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times were farr off, are made nigh by the bloud of Chriſt. Chriſts benefits to us, are like the oyntment<note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 133.2.</note> on <hi>Aarons</hi> head, that ran downe on his beard, and deſcended to the skirts of his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; they went downe to the loweſt members of the Church. When he was upon the earth hee ſhewed his love unto the poore, in doing good to the Halt, the Lame, the Blind, as it were ſo many cripples from ſeverall Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls. Now love<note n="n" place="margin">Doctor <hi>Boys</hi> expo. of the <hi>Creed.</hi>
               </note> is more ſhewed in deeds then in words: but more in ſuffering, then it is in doing, ſo that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152100:39"/>the love of Chriſt was eſpecially ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto us in dying for us. As the Father ſhewed great love in giving his Sonne unto us; ſo the ſon ſhewed like equall love in being ſo ready to ſuffer for us. Greater<note n="o" place="margin">John 15 13.</note> love hath no man then this, that a man lay downe his life for his friends; but Chriſt ſuffered for us <hi>dum inimici eſſemus</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 5.8, 10.</note>, while wee were ſinners, and enemies, and gave himſelfe to death for us, while wee were<note n="q" place="margin">Eph 2.1.</note> dead in treſpaſſes and ſins. Wee read of ſome indeed that have been rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to dy for their friends, as<note n="r" place="margin">Cicer. Offic.</note> 
               <hi>Damon</hi> for his <hi>Pithyas; Pylades</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m de Amici</note> for his <hi>Orestes,</hi> of whom the Poet.<note n="t" place="margin">Ovid.</note>.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Extitit hoc unum quod non convenerat illis,</l>
               <l>Hic negat, in<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vicem pugnat uter<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mori.</l>
            </q>
            <p>They never fell our about any thing but this, which of them ſhould firſt lay downe his life for the other. And wee read of ſome that have dyed for others, as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> reports<note n="v" place="margin">De Civitate Dei li. <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>5</hi>
               </note> of <hi>Castor</hi> and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152100:40"/>
               <hi>Pollux</hi> the ſons of <hi>Tyndarus,</hi> that <hi>Pollux</hi> intreated to impart halfe his life on his brother. And we read that <hi>Codrus</hi> did willingly<note n="w" place="margin">Iuſtin.</note> dy for his countrey. And alſo it is reported<note n="x" place="margin">Iuvenall.</note> 
               <hi>Subeuntem fata mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti Alcesten:</hi> that <hi>Alcestes</hi> did undergo the deſtinies of her husband, and by her death redeemed his life. Theſe ſhewed great loves in laying downe their lives, but it was for them that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them as much, or had deſerved ſo much at their hands: But Chriſt layd downe his life for us, not onely <hi>Sine noſtris meritis, ſed cum nostris demeritis</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">In <hi>Cant.</hi> Ser. 15</note>, when we deſerved no love, but when we deſerved as much hatred from him as was due unto his enemies; and extended the fruits of that love, and the benefits of that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to all that will lay hold upon them. It is written of the <hi>Cherubins</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">1 Kings 6.27.</note> that they ſtretched out their wings, <hi>ad parietes uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>,</hi> to the wall on each ſide, full ten cubits ſo Chriſt being
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152100:40"/>ſtretched forth upon the Croſſe, exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his benefits to the ends of the World: hee ſtood open to receive all commers, and ſpread forth the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of his love unto all, therein reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling the leaves of the <hi>Lilies of the Valleyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the <hi>Lily, Lactei floris herba, unde &amp; nuncupata, quaſi lidia,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iſidore,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Orig. lib. <hi>17</hi> cap <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>cujus cum candor ſit in foliis, auri tamen ſpecies intus effulget.</hi> The <hi>Lily</hi> is a milke white Flower; from whence it takes its denomination from the whitenes of it, and the whitenes of the <hi>Lily</hi> may ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify Chriſts eternity. And therefore S. <hi>Iohn</hi> the divine deſcribing the parts of Chriſts Body, ſayes<note n="b" place="margin">Rev. 1.14</note> his Head, and his Haires were white like Wooll, as white as Snow; for though,<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Perkins</hi> on the Rev.</note> as hee is man he had a beginning, yet in regard of his God-head he is eternall, and is therefore called<note n="d" place="margin">Dan. 7.22.</note> the ancient of dayes; there is nothing more ancient then he: for he had a being when all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152100:41"/>were not, being begotten of his Father before all time. And therefore the <hi>Arrian</hi> out of his envious pride<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sidenham Ser.</hi> on John 8.50.</note> is at once bountifull and injurious, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to inveſt Chriſt with the title <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but diſrobes him of that glorious title, and his owne, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, granting him a like eſſence with the Father, not the ſame, equall to him in power, not eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: for if he bee a ſonne (ſaith he) he muſt be borne, and if borne, there was a time when there was no ſonne.</p>
            <p>Indeed it is true according to the courſe of nature, but this is ſo farre above it, that<note n="f" place="margin">Eſ. 53.8.</note> who can declare it? <hi>Cum natum confitemur, non tamen non na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum praedicamus,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Hilary</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">De Trin. li. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note>. When we confeſſe that he was borne, we do not ſay that he was not borne. For <hi>ubi author aeternus est, ibi &amp; nativitatis aeternitas eſt,</hi> Where the author of the birth is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, there is alſo an eternity of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, and from an eternall begetter
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152100:41"/>proceeds an eternall begetting. Indeed the Word<note n="h" place="margin">John 1.14</note> was made fleſh, but <hi>non amiſerat quod erat, ſed coeperat eſſe quod non erat,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">De Trin. li. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> ſaith the ſame Father hee cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not to be what he was before, but he began to be in a new manner that he was not before. The name <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Iehovah,</hi> derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Havah fuit,</hi> he was, (in which name all time paſt, preſent, and to come is comprehended, as the <hi>Rabbins</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cay on Ex. apal A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth.</note> have obſerved) is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto Chriſt, who is called <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.6. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Iehovah tſidkenu</hi>) the Lord our righteouſnes: intimating that hee is the ſame GOD that is<note n="l" place="margin">Rev. 1.8.</note> that was, <hi>ab aeterno,</hi> from all eternity, and will be in <hi>aeternum</hi> to all eternity. Hee being the ſame yeſterday<note n="m" place="margin">Heb. 13.8.</note> before his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, to day, at his comming, and for ever, even at his comming againe. Heare Chriſt teſtifying of himſelfe;<note n="n" place="margin">Joh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 5.26.</note> as the Father hath life in himſelfe, ſo hath he given to the Son to have life in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. <hi>Apertiſsime docet</hi> (ſaith Saint
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152100:42"/>
               <hi>Cyrill</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Theſaur. lib. <hi>10.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quod ſicut pater in ſeipſo aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naliter vitam habet, ſic &amp; filius aeternali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vitam in ſeipſo habet.</hi> As the Father hath life eternally in himſelfe, ſo hath the Son life eternally in himſelfe. As he was man<note n="p" place="margin">Athanaſ. Creed.</note> of the ſubſtance of his Mother, borne in the World, ſo was he God of the ſubſtance of his Father, begotten before the Worlds, for hee is eternall; being the <hi>white Lily of the Valleys.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whitenes more properly ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies innocency, and therefore the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines</hi> call innocency <hi>candor,</hi> which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies whitenes, and innocent men, <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didi,</hi> white men: and the holy Ghoſt ſeemes to allow it; for the Church is ſaid<note n="q" place="margin">Rev. 19.8.</note> to be arrayed in fine linnen, cleane and white, which is the righteouſnes (or innocency) of the Saints. Seeing then that <hi>folia liliorum ſunt puriſsima, &amp; tam intus quam extra candidiſsima,</hi> the <hi>Lily</hi> is moſt pure and white both with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and without, it fitly reſembles the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152100:42"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nnocency both of Chriſts nature and action. <hi>Nigra ſunt vitia, virtus candida est,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bern.</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">In <hi>Cant.</hi> Ser. 7.</note> vices are blacke, but vertue is white. So that <hi>Cicero</hi> might well affirme,<note n="ſ" place="margin">De legibus li. <hi>2</hi>
               </note> that <hi>Color albus praecipuè decorus Deo eſt:</hi> the whiteſt colour is moſt agreeable to the higheſt Son of <hi>GOD. Abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> liliis nunquam est, qui abſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que vitiis ſemper est.</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Div. Bern. ubi ſupr.</note> He is never with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whitenes of the <hi>Lily,</hi> that is ever without the blacknes of ſinne. Hee is fayrer then<note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 45.2.</note> the children of men: And it may more truely be ſayd of him then it was of <hi>Abſolom</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">2 Sam. 14.25.</note>: But in all <hi>Iſrael</hi> there was none to be prayſed ſo much for his beauty: from the ſole of his foot, even to the crowne of the Head there was no blemiſh in him. Chriſt was a Lambe<note n="x" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.19.</note>: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, without blemiſh and without ſpot: without<note n="y" place="margin">Lorin. in <hi>Pet.</hi>
               </note> blemiſh of originall ſin, and without the ſpot of actuall. There could bee no ſpot found in his action, nor blemiſh in his converſation. But ſome may
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152100:43"/>object and ſay, Chriſt tooke upon him the defects and infirmities of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which in us are oft ſinfull, and ſo they might be in him. To this <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas</hi> anſwers,<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Par.</hi> 3. <hi>qu.</hi> 15. <hi>Art.</hi> 1.</note> Chriſt tooke our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects upon him to make ſatiſfaction for us, to manifeſt the truth of his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature, or to be a perfect pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of vertue unto us. But hee could not take upon him any ſinfull defects for any of theſe cauſes. For Firſt, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full defects could not make ſatiſfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for ſinne, as being that wherewith God is diſpleaſed. Secondly, ſin coul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not manifeſt the truth of his human<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for ſinne belongs not to the natur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of man, but is rather contrary unto it for that was good and made by Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but ſin is evill, and was brought in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Devill. Thirdly, it could be not ample of vertue, as being contrary u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it. But Chriſt tooke not on him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the defects of mans nature, for firſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> tooke not on him<note n="a" place="margin">Nicol d Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <hi>3.</hi> Sente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtinct. <hi>16</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>defectus vitioſos,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152100:43"/>poenales,</hi> not the defects of ſinne, as ignorance, and pronenes to evill, which was impoſſible that hee ſhould bee ſubject unto; but ſuch defects as were puniſhments for ſinne, as hunger, thirſt, &amp;c. Secondly, hee tooke upon him not <hi>defectus perſonales, ſed natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> not perſonall defects, that accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany ſome particular perſons, but uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall, that accompany mans nature. But the defects in him did differ from ours in three<note n="b" place="margin">Auguſt de Civitat. Dei. li. <hi>14</hi> cap <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> reſpects. Firſt, <hi>reſpectu effectus,</hi> in regard of the effect, in us they often diſturb reaſon, but in him they did not. Secondly, <hi>reſpectu prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipii,</hi> in reſpect of the beginning or cauſe of them, in us they often goe before the judgement of reaſon, but in Chriſt they were alwayes ſubject to reaſons command. Thirdly, <hi>reſpectu objecti,</hi> in regard of the object, in us affection is not alwaies voyd of fault, being often carryed upon unlawfull objects, but in Chriſt it was not ſo,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152100:44"/>his were like water put into a pure Glaſſe, and ours like water put into a veſſell beſmeared with durt, the more we ſtirre it, the dirtier it is. So that (notwithſtanding his defects that hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ooke from us) wee may ſay of him with the Apoſtle<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.</note> Though hee were touched with our infirmities, and in all poynts tempted as wee are; yet was hee without ſinne. God ſent his Sonne<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 8 3.</note> in the likenes of ſinfull fleſh, fleſh in truth, but ſinfull fleſh in likenes, not but that hee was ſo farre from ſinne<note n="e" place="margin">Six. Sen. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>244</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>3.</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>3</hi>
               </note> that he had no incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation unto it. The firſt <hi>Adam</hi> did (as I may ſo ſpeake) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> on Pet 2.22.</note> make ſin in the World, the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> did take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſins of the World<note n="g" place="margin">John 1.29.</note>; and it was neceſſary that hee that ſhould ſatiſfy for the ſins of others, ſhould bee free from ſinne himſelfe. The firſt <hi>Adam</hi> had a <hi>poſſe non peccare,</hi> a power not to ſinne, but the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> had a <hi>non poſſe peccare,</hi> no power
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152100:44"/>at all to ſin, but hee was.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Integer vitae, ſceleriſque purus</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Horace.</note>; Hee did no ſin, neither was guile<note n="i" place="margin">1 Pet 2.22</note> found in his mouth. Neither was it ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to manifeſt the whitenes of his innocency, that hee was free from ſin, but hee was full of holines alſo. <hi>Semper manet ſanctus in verbis, ſanctus in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus ſuis, ſanctus in omnibus volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus ſuis,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Cyrill</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">In Levit li. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> Chriſt was alwayes holy in his <hi>words,</hi> holy in his <hi>workes,</hi> holy in his affections. And becauſe a ſinner cannot make ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for his owne ſins, therefore hee ought to be holy<note n="l" place="margin">Parae. in Heb.</note> not legally onely, as the Leviticall <hi>Priests</hi> were holy, being conſecrated by their legall ſacrifices; but morally alſo, which the Apoſtle ſetts downe<note n="m" place="margin">Heb 7 26</note> in foure <hi>Epithetes.</hi> Firſt, hee ſayes hee is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſanctus,</hi> holy. Secondly, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>innocens,</hi> innocent, free from all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall corruption which the <hi>Prieſts</hi> of the Law were ſubject unto as well as the people. Thirdly, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>impollutus,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:152100:45"/>not defiled with any actuall ſinne. Fourthly, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſegrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus à peccatoribus,</hi> ſeparated from ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: that is; guilty of no puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment due unto ſinners by the Law. So that his challenge made to his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies muſt needs ſtand good, Which of you<note n="n" place="margin">John 8.46.</note> convinceth me of ſin. <hi>Habet hoc verbum Chriſti magnam fiduciam,</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Origen.</hi>)<note n="o" place="margin">In Iohan.</note> 
               <hi>cum nullus hominum fidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialiter hoc dicere potuerit, niſi ſolus Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus noſter qui peccatum non fecit.</hi> This ſaying of Chriſt is ſpoken with great confidence, and carryes credit with it, ſeeing no man could ſay ſo much truely of himſelfe, but only our Lord which did no ſin. What was ſaid of <hi>Iob</hi> might be ſayd of him<note n="p" place="margin">Job 1.22.</note>; In all (that hee did) hee ſinned not, neither char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged God fooliſhly <hi>i, e,</hi> wickedly. His innocency hath been cleered many ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations ſince (even by his worſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies) by <hi>Pilate</hi> that condemned him, who accknowledgeth that<note n="q" place="margin">Luke 23.14, 22.</note> hee
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152100:45"/>could finde no fault in him, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth him guiltles three times, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he doth condemne him as guilty. And by <hi>Iudas</hi> that betrayed him, who confeſſed that hee had ſinned<note n="r" place="margin">Mat. 27 4.</note> in that hee had betrayed innocent bloud. So that when <hi>Herod,</hi> and his men of warre<note n="ſ" place="margin">Luke 23.11.</note> arrayed Chriſt in a gorgeous (or white) Robe, they did therein after a myſticall manner ſufficiently teſtify both the excellent dignity, and the innocent probity of the man, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring plainly againſt themſelves, that Chriſt ſhould rather have been acquitted as an innocent, then condemned as a malefactour, for in his innocency he did reſemble the white colour of the <hi>Lily of the Vallies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the <hi>Lily</hi> growes and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth among Thornes, ſo Chriſt when hee was upon the Earth was converſant among ſinners. Hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed with ſinners, though hee were free from ſinne. And this ſence ſome
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152100:46"/>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Angtlon. in loc.</note> expound this part of the Text. <hi>Vbi per incarnationis ſacramentum, huc in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vallem lachrymarum, inter ſpinas &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſortia peccatorum deſcendit, lilium effectum ſe eſſe teſtatur.</hi> When Chriſt by the myſtery of his incarnation, did deſcend into this valley of teares, among thorns and ſinners he ſhewed himſelfe, to be the <hi>Lily of the Vallies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Phariſees did wonder to ſee Chriſt u,<note n="v" place="margin">Mat. 9.11.</note> eating with Publicans and ſinners but it was no greater marvell to ſee our Saviour Chriſt converſant upon earth among ſinners, teaching them, then it was to ſee the Devill with our firſt parents in Paradice, tempting them. He was the Phyſitian of ſoules (as you have already heard,) and ſinners were his beſt patients, and why then ſhould he forſake their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany? No, hee ſhuns them not, but hee converſeth with them, and feeds with them, and calls them to come to be cured. <hi>Miraris Iudaee</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſologus</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:152100:46"/>
               <note n="w" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ser.</hi> 29.</note>) <hi>cur Christus miſceatur convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vio peccatorum, qui propter peccatores &amp; naſci voluit, &amp; non recuſavit occidi? Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tras cur peccatorum Vinum bibat, qui pro peccatoribus ſuum ſanguinem fudit?</hi> doſt thou admire (O thou Iew) why Chriſt ſhould eat with ſinners, who would bee borne for ſinners, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed not to dye for them? Doſt thou murmure that he wil drink the wine of ſinners, which poured out his blood for ſinners? What marvell is it, if hee doth eate at the table with ſinners, that ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red death on the Croſſe for them. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did the Phyſitian leave the patient that hee would heale, nor God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the ſinner that hee would ſave? It was Chriſts office<note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 9.13.</note> not to call the righteous but ſinners to repentance: not the righteous, for there were none ſo righteous, that have no need of his comming: <hi>Si homo non periiſſet, filius ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis non veniſſet,</hi> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auguſtin</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">de Tempor. Ser. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note>, If man had not ſinned, the Sonne of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152100:47"/>man had not come: or elſe not to call the righteous, <hi>ironice,</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Chryſ. Hierom apud Barrad.</note> that is, not the Scribes and Phariſees which did juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie themſelves, and thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to have no need of the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, but were juſt and righteous in their owne conceits, thinking all to bee bad but themſelves. Like unto whom were thoſe Heretickes the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Euſebius Pamph <hi>Eccles</hi> Hiſt.</note> in the primitive Church, that thought themſelves (onely) to bee pure, and accounted all to bee ſinfull but onely thoſe that were of their owne impure ſect: And theſe were the Fathers and predeceſſors of the factious <hi>Schiſmatickes</hi> who (at this day) do walke in their ſteps, accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all reprobates, but them of their owne tribe. But he calls thoſe ſinners, that feeling their ſins acknowledge themſelves to bee ſinfull. But as the <hi>Lily</hi> (though it grow among Thorns) yet it loſeth none of the whiteneſſe of his colour, or fragrancy of its
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152100:47"/>ſmell: ſo Chriſt, though hee conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed among thorny ſinners, yet hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned ſtill his innocency: neither did hee converſe with them<note n="b" place="margin">Janſen <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cor. cap.</hi> 33.</note> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme them in their ſinnes, but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert them from them. Though hee did goe upon<note n="c" place="margin">Prov. 6 28.</note> coales, yet was he not burnt. Though hee touched pitch<note n="d" place="margin">Eccleſ. 13.1.</note>, yet was hee not defiled with it: though hee had fellowſhip with the proud, yet was not hee like unto them, though hee were converſant with thornie ſinners, yet was hee not infected with their ſins, that kept on ſtill the white Robes of his innocency; therein reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling the nature of the <hi>Lily of the Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys:</hi> And now, I come to the limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his ſecond attribute to the firſt ſubject <hi>(of the Valleys) I am the Roſe of Sharon,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Chriſt is not<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Doctor</hi> Dove in Loc.</note> the lofty <hi>Cedar,</hi> but the lowly <hi>Lily;</hi> not of the high Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, but of the low valleys, that is, humility it ſelfe, <hi>Suorum Deus altiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152100:48"/>fuorum Christus humillimus</hi> as God of all others is a patterne of Majeſty, ſo Chriſt of all others is a ſpectacle of humility; Hee was an example of humility in theſe reſpects<note n="f" place="margin">Auguſt. de Civ. Dei. li. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note>: <hi>naſcendo, converſando, praedicando, miracula faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endo, &amp; moriendo;</hi> In his birth, in his converſation, in his preaching, in his working of miracles, and in his dying. Firſt, in his birth, Hee choſe not his deſcent from the mighty Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs of <hi>Aſſyria, Greece,</hi> and <hi>Perſia,</hi> but of the contemptible and deſpiſed <hi>Iewes:</hi> and among them hee choſe not any rich Parents to bee borne of, but a poore <hi>Virgin,</hi> eſpouſed to a poore <hi>Carpenter.</hi> What greater abaſement could there bee, then that hee which thundred in the Cloudes, ſhould cry in the Cradle? that hee ſhould put off the glorious Robes of his immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite, and put on the baſe ragges of our mortality; that hee which was cloathed with Majeſty and honour,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152100:48"/>ſhould bee cloathed with ſwadling clowtes; that hee that in Heaven was GOD not ſubject to his Father, in earth ſhould bee man ſubject to his Mother; that <hi>Mary</hi> that was a ſheepe, ſhould bring forth a <hi>Sheepherd;</hi> that hee which was the Father of <hi>Mary</hi> ſhould become the ſoone of <hi>Mary;</hi> this myſtery is ſo great, and the humility ſo wonderfull, that, as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, it<note n="g" place="margin">In vrgil. Nativ.</note> is <hi>mirabiliter ſingulare, &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulariter mirabile,</hi> wonderfully ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and ſingularly wonderfull. There is ſo great humility in CHRISTS birth, that S. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaith<note n="h" place="margin">Ser. <hi>18.</hi> Nat</note>, <hi>Omnis bujus nativitatis ſchola, humilitatis est <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fficina,</hi> the whole Schoole of Chriſts nativity, is a ſhop of humility. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, hee ſhewed his humility in his converſation, becauſe though hee did no ſinne<note n="i" place="margin">Deſtruct. vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, yet hee tooke upon him the puniſhments for ſinne, moſt humb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y undertaking the infirmities of the body, and defects of the ſoule (that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152100:49"/>are not ſinfull) as to bee weary, hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, ſorrowfull, &amp;c. And though he were Lord of all, yet hee becomes ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to his owne Diſciples, and<note n="k" place="margin">John 13.5.</note> waſheth their feete, telling them<note n="l" place="margin">Luke 22.27.</note> that hee is among them as one that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth. Whence ſome<note n="m" place="margin">Barrad. Stella</note> conjecture, that Chriſt did uſe to ſerve them being at meat. Thirdly, hee ſhewed his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility in his preaching, becauſe hee ſought not his owne glory, but the glory of him that ſent him. And hee tells his Diſciples<note n="n" place="margin">John 14 10.</note>, The words that I ſpeake unto you, I ſpeake not of my ſelfe. And when hee choſe his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to preach unto the World, hee choſe not rich and learned men, but poore ſimple ſilly Fiſher-men. Had Chriſt choſen ſuch as <hi>Aristotle,</hi> and <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> to preach the Goſpell, they would have ſayd, they were ſo lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that they might eaſily convince; they were ſo eloquence that they might eaſily perſwade: but hee choſe unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152100:49"/>Fiſher-men to confound the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Phyloſophers, that the glory might not be given to the meanes. Forthly, hee ſhewed his humility in his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of miracles; becauſe when hee did great miracles, hee commands the parties on whom they were wrought, not to divulge them. When hee cured one of the leproſy<note n="o" place="margin">Mat. 8.4.</note>, and reſtored ſight to the blind man<note n="p" place="margin">Marke 8 26.</note>, hee chargeth them to tell no man. <hi>Mundavit leproſum Dominus, &amp; juſsit eum nulli hoc fateri, hoc fateri, docens quam eſſet alienus ab aura gloriae, pompa<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> jactantiae,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſostome</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Apud Barrad</note>; In doing thoſe miracles which Chriſt would not have told, he ſhewed how farre hee was from vayne glory, and ſeeking prayſe of men; but in thoſe miracles that hee would have to bee divulged, hee ſhewes how free hee was in ſeeking glory to GOD: for hee bidds the man that was freed from his legion of divells, to ſhew<note n="r" place="margin">Luke 8.39.</note> how great things (not hee) but God had
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152100:50"/>done for him. And all the time of his life wherein hee wrought his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, hee went abour doing of them; he rode not in any ſtately manner, but went on foot: neither do I read that hee did ride at all, but once, when hee rode upon an Aſſe<note n="s" place="margin">Mat. 21.25.</note> into <hi>Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when he ſate, <hi>Nunquam in ſede, nec in pulvinari, ſed in ipſa ſuperficie terrae, modo in montibus, modo apud fontes ſedet &amp; docet,</hi> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Chryſoſtome;</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Hom. <hi>67.</hi> in Mat.</note>; Chriſt ſate and taught, not on any couch or chayre of ſtate, ſometimes on the mountaines, ſometimes by the fountaines, alwaies on the <hi>ſuperficies</hi> of the earth. Fiftly Chriſt ſhewed his humiltty in his dying. It was great love, and as great Humility for him, to be cloathed with the vaile of our nature, and to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the infirmities of our feeble na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; yet it was greater love (and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility too) for him, to be compaſſed with the ſhadow of death, and to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152100:50"/>undergoe the penalty due to our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full nature. What humilitie could bee greater then that the Lord of life ſhould ſuffer a ſhamefull and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minious death? that hee that was <hi>gloria Angelorum,</hi> ſhould become <hi>oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brium hominum?</hi> he that was the glory of Angells, ſhould be made the<note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 22 6.</note> ſcorn of men, and deſpiſed of the people? Thus Chriſt (knowing that humilitie did ſuite well with the head, when the body was ſicke with pride) bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.<note n="w" place="margin">Pſal 18.9.</note> the heavens and came downe; there was the humilitie of his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, not putting it off, but clothing it with the raggs of fleſh: And from his birth to his buriall, from the time of his being borne in another mans ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able, untill the time of his being bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed in another mans tombe, he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſhewed the humility of his manhood, never ceaſing untill his head were laid under the earth, his foot-ſtoole. So that wee may ſay of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152100:51"/>him with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">De Paſs. Dom.</note>, <hi>Nemo illo ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mior, nemo humilior,</hi> there was none more lofty, none more lowly; none more high, and none more humble then he: he humbled himſelfe (ſaith the Apoſtle)<note n="y" place="margin">Philip. 2.8.</note> and became obedient unto death, even the death of the Croſſe, in all his humilitie ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe to bee <hi>the Lily of the Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now becauſe it is not enough for us to feede on the Word, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> might<note n="z" place="margin">Deut. 23, 24, 25.</note> on their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Grapes, and Corne, while they were in their Vine-yards, or Fields, but might carry none away with them; I ſhall (briefly) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhake ſome of the Boughes, and give ſome of the Fruit (of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> which hath been delivered) to ever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one that will carry it away with him Firſt, therefore, in that CHRIST re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembles the Flower of the <hi>Lilies,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> open towards Heaven, but cloſe an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:152100:51"/>ſhut towards earth, wee may from thence learne to know the ſeat of our affection: to ſet our affections<note n="a" place="margin">Col. 3.1, 2.</note> on things above, and to ſeeke thoſe things, and not the things on earth. Chriſtians receive their name from Chriſt. <hi>Et operae pretium est, quod ſicut ſunt haeredes nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, ita ſint imitatores ſanctitatis,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Semen. pag. <hi>496.</hi>
               </note>: It is fit, that as they are heires of his name, ſo they ſhould bee imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of his nature and converſation. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſatio autem Chriſti apertè docet praeſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia contemnere, &amp; ad futura ſpem dirigere,</hi> ſaith the ſame Father<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag</hi> 17. 23.</note>. But the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of Chriſt doth plainly teach us to contemne preſent riches, and to love future, not to mind things preſent, but to place our hopes on things to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome. Secondly, let us ſhew our love to Chriſt by pitty and compaſſion. Chriſt (reſembling the leaves of the <hi>Lilies</hi>) did extend his love downeward toward us: let us extend our love up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward toward him. As Chriſt ſhewed
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152100:52"/>his love every way to us, ſo let us ſhew our love every way to him: hee loved us even when hee was dying, let us love him all the time wee are living. <hi>Christus quanto pro me vilior, tanto mihi charior,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">In <hi>Epiph. Ser.</hi> 1.</note>: The more vile the Sonne of God was made for us, ſo much the more deare ſhould hee bee unto us. <hi>Domine Ieſu, dilexisti me plus quam te, quoniam mori voluiſti pro me &amp;c. pudeat non redamare te pro tanto amore tuo</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
               </note> O Lord Ieſu, thou haſt loved me more than thy ſelfe, in that thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt vouchſafe to dy for me: it would be a great ſhame for me, not to love thee againe for this thy ſo great love. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Chriſt was an example for us to imitate in our converſation: and that in three reſpects. Firſt, in innocency; we may learne from him to bee<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 10.16.</note> wiſe as Serpents, and innocent as Doves. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, as Chriſt was converſant with ſinners, but not defiled with ſinne; ſo though wee live in the midſt of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152100:52"/>generation with <hi>Noah,</hi> yet let us not participate with the evill of the time, or place, or company where wee live. I doe but touch of theſe things by way of application to this ſubject, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I muſt ſpeake more of them by way of explication in the next. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and laſtly, Chriſt is a patterne unto us of humility. Remember that Chriſt is a <hi>Lily of the Vallies.</hi> God<note n="g" place="margin">Angelom in loc.</note> is the God of humble men, and humility was taught us from him by precept and patterne. <hi>Puderet te forſan imitari homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem humilem, ſaltem imitare humilem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Austin.</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> John Tract. 23.</note> Thou wouldſt bee aſhamed (perhaps) to imitate an humble man, yet at leaſt imitate a hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble God. Men are ready to allow Court faſhions, and the greater the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage, the ſonner is the faſhion fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed: Now Chriſt our King tooke on him the faſhion of humility, and all that meane to bee accepted in his court muſt weare the ſame faſhion. For <hi>Quid
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152100:53"/>deteſtandum amplius, quid gravius puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endum, quam ut videns deum coeli parvu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum factum, ultra apponat homo magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care ſe ſupra terram? Intolerabilis impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentiae eſt, ut ubi ſeſe exinanivit Majestas, vermiculus infletur &amp; intumeſcat,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Flores Born. pag. <hi>2133.</hi>
               </note>; What is more to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted, what more worthy to be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, then that man, which ſeeing the God of Heaven to become little on earth, ſhould exalt himſelfe above earth? It is an intolerable impudency that where Majeſty became low, a Worme ſhould ſwell and thinke to bee great. The Diſciple<note n="k" place="margin">Mat. 10.24.</note> is not greater then his Maſter, nor the ſervant above his Lord; <hi>Vt exaltari voluit ſicut Dominus &amp; humiliari noluit ſicut ſervus</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c. Mural.</note> That hee ſhould be exalted as his Lord, that will not bee humbled as a ſervant. And therefore, <hi>Si vis capere celſitudinem Dei, cape prius humilitatem Christi,</hi> is the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Saint <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Epiſt.</note>; If thou deſireſt to bee partaker of the glory of God,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152100:53"/>follow Chriſt in the ſteps of humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, through this valley of miſery, that thou mayſt aſcend to him to the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of Majeſty. <hi>Which GOD grant wee may all doe, for Ieſus Chriſts ſake. To whom with the Father, and the Bleſſed Spirit, bee all honour and glory, now and for ever more,</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:152100:54"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152100:54"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. RICHARD FENN, Knight, Lord Major of the City of <hi>London;</hi> And to <hi>the right Worſhipfull, the Master,</hi> Wardens and Aſſiſtants of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of HABERDASHERS, <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> May perhaps by ſome bee accounted a right Son of <hi>Levi</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Numb. 16.7.</note>, in taking too much upon mee, to preſent this <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> to your <hi>Patronage (Right Worſhipfull)</hi> But it hath ſome right and title to you, who ſhew your ſelves to bee members of the <hi>Church,</hi> in
<pb facs="tcp:152100:55"/>extending your charitie to them that are farre off. For you doe not take delight, as <hi>Cyrus</hi> did,<note n="b" place="margin">Xenophon.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in putting men in good hopes, but in doing good deeds, &amp; allowing good helpes, to maintaine manie of the Sonnes of the <hi>Prophets.</hi> Among the reſt J was one that had an exhibition from your <hi>Company,</hi> while I lived in the <hi>Univerſity.</hi> This I could not forget, and therefore, though I cannot doe any thing by way of requitall with <hi>David</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">1 Kings 2.7.</note> to <hi>Barzillai,</hi> &amp; <hi>Jonathan</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">2 Sam. 9.7.</note>, yet J must ever by way of thankefull acknowledgement, pray for your ſociety, as S. <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:152100:55"/>did for the houſe of <hi>Oneſipho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">2 Tim. 1.16.</note>. The <hi>Lord</hi> give mercie unto you all, and grant that you may all finde mercie of the <hi>Lord</hi> in that day.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors, and Worſhips to bee commanded in all Chriſtian duties, WILLIAM PARKES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="lecture">
            <pb facs="tcp:152100:56"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152100:56"/>
            <head>THE ROSE AND LILY.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>SOLOMONS SONG. 2.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>J am the <hi>Roſe</hi> of Sharon, and the <hi>Lily</hi> of the vallyes.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen <hi>Balak</hi> brought <hi>Balaam</hi> to the top of <hi>Piſgah</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Numbers 23.13 14.</note>, hee ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him onely the utmoſt part of the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but did not ſhew him all: ſo may I ſay unto you, I have brought you (as it were) to the top of <hi>Piſgah,</hi> whence you have ſeene
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152100:57"/>(onely) the utmoſt part of thoſe my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries that concerne our Saviour Chriſt; but cannot ſhew you all. Wee have all this while but floated on this deepe Ocean, we are not able to fadome it. It is as much impoſſible for the wit and learning of one man (though he have<note n="b" place="margin">Pſ 45.1.</note> the Pen of a ready writer, and<note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 13.1.</note> ſpeake with the tongue of men and Angels) fully to comprehend and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe thoſe myſteries, as it is for a Boy to empty the Ocean Sea with an Oy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-ſhell. And therefore as the Payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Tymanthes,</hi> being to expreſſe <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamemnons</hi> griefe conceived for the loſſe of his daughter <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> drew him with his face covered over with a veyle, that men might conceive of that ſorrow which hee could not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe: ſo I, being to ſpeake of thoſe great myſteries of Chriſts paſſion, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, humility, and the reſt, muſt needs have paſſed many things over with the veyle of ſilence, as being
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152100:57"/>not able perfectly to decipher them. Now then give mee leave to alter the ſubject of my <hi>Text,</hi> and to leave it as it concernes Chriſt, and to follow it as it reſpects the Church, for of that ſubject (the Church) doe ſome<note n="d" place="margin">Caldee Para. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hrast, Arnſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woreth B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in loc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the <hi>Text,</hi> as you formerly were alſo told. For what is written of <hi>Ianus,</hi> that hee had two faces, <hi>praeterita reto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiciens, futura proſpiciens,</hi> looking two wayes, forwards and backwards: ſo may I ſay of this <hi>Text,</hi> it hath two faces, one looking toward Chriſt, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther toward the Church. I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ady (in ſome meaſure) unveyled that, that lookes upon Chriſt, and now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt unmaske that, which lookes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owne on the Church. As I have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> how Chriſt doth, ſo now I muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ew you wherein the Church doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſemble the <hi>Roſe of Sharon, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ly of the Vallies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe the ſpouſe ought to bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rreſpondent to the husband, the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152100:58"/>members to be proportionable to the head, and the myſticall body of Chriſt conformable to himſelfe, therefore I ſhall not need to ſeeke out any new and untrodden path, but follow the ſame way I have already gone. Firſt therefore, as the rednes and prickles of the <hi>Roſe</hi> did repreſent Chriſts paſſion, ſo doth it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the Churches trouble and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution; Secondly the ſweet ſmell of the <hi>Roſe</hi> doth intimate the Churches ſweet converſation upon earth: and Thirdly the <hi>Roſes</hi> being dead in winter, but budding out againe, ſhewes the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection from the dead: Firſt, of the firſt: as the <hi>Roſe</hi> is full of prickles ſo is the Church alwayes ſubject to perſecution.</p>
            <p>The ſweetenes of the <hi>Roſe</hi> is joyned with prickles which doth plainly teach that, <hi>Quae jucunda vobis ſunt (O homines) triſtibus permixta ſunt,</hi> ſaith St. Bazill<note n="e" place="margin">Hom. de Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſo.</note> ſweet and ſowre, mirth and mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning are intermixed together in this
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152100:58"/>life, <hi>Nocte pluit tota, redeunt ſpectacula mane,</hi> ſaith the Poet<note n="f" place="margin">Virgil.</note>; Weeping may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure for a night, but joy commeth in the Morning, ſaith the Prophet<note n="g" place="margin">Pſ. 30.5.</note>, <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> was one day renowned in the Senate, accounted a <hi>Pater patriae,</hi> a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his Country; often <hi>Praetor,</hi> and inveſted with princely honour; The next day, (as it were) you may ſee him looſe his honour, and bee reputed a tyrant, accounted no <hi>pater patriae,</hi> but <hi>hoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is patriae,</hi> no father of his countrey, but a factor againſt it, no <hi>Praetor</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it, but <hi>praedator,</hi> a preyer upon it to ſpoyle it, not ſaluted, but ſlaine in the Senate, and from an Emperour turned to a dead carkaſſe. Our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt himſelfe when hee was u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the earth did find this intercourſe of things, for upon Mount <hi>Tabor</hi> hee was transfigured with glory that his face did ſhine, upon Mount <hi>Calvary</hi> hee was diſfigured with ſorrow that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion did cover his face, and ſuch is the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152100:59"/>condition of man in this life, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he is lifted up on the Mountaines of proſperity, and ſometimes hee is caſt downe into the valley of adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: ſometimes hee walkes in the ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine of peace and plenty, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the ſhade of trouble and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution. But the Church doth uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lie open to that laſh: for a ſhort ſpace (indeed) ſhe had peace under the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Constantine,</hi> but preſently in the time of <hi>Arrius</hi> ſhee was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with perſecution. To <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple there was <hi>purpureus aſcenſus,</hi> as the latine verſion renders it<note n="h" place="margin">Cant. 3.10.</note>, a cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of purple<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that Temple was a type of the Church, and the covering ſhewes that it weares the colour of the <hi>Roſe. Oportebat Christum pati,</hi> It beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Chriſt to ſuffer<note n="i" place="margin">Luke 24.46.</note>, and afterward to enter into his glory: muſt hee ſuffer before hee could enter into his owne glory, and is the Diſciple greater then his Maſter, to thinke to come thither
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152100:59"/>without it? <hi>Christi nativitas à martyriis infantum ſtatim coepit, per quod oſtenſum eſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Cyprian</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Ad Thibarit de exhar. mart. Epiſt. <hi>56.</hi> pag. <hi>126.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>neminem eſſe à pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riculo perſecutionis immunem. Quam ergo gravis cauſa ſit hominis Christiani, ſervum pati nolle, cum prior paſsus ſit dominus? &amp; pro peccatis noſtris nos pati nolle, cum peccatum ſuum proprium non habens, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſit ille pro nobis.</hi> The martyrdome of Infants did follow preſently after the birth of Chriſt, by which is ſhewed that there is no member of the Church free from the prickles of perſecution. And how grievous is the caſe of a chriſtian man, that the ſervant will not ſuffer when his Lord hath ſuffered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him? that we ſhould not ſuffer for our ſins, when he that did no ſin, ſuffered for us? <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke was toſſed up and down by the waves of the floud, &amp; reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not untill it lighted on the<note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 8.4.</note> Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of <hi>Ararat;</hi> that Arke was a type of the Church, which is toſſed up &amp; down in the Sea of this World by the waves of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152100:60"/>perſecution one wave following in the necke of another, and findeth no reſt, untill it come to that mountaine of holineſſe, that haven of happineſſe where it would be. <hi>Perſecutio nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam deeſt Chriſtiano, neque &amp; Chriſto,</hi> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Ia Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>verſ. Paul pag. <hi>68.</hi>
               </note>, as Chriſt was not, ſo the Church muſt not looke to bee free from perſecution. <hi>Erras, frater, erras, ſi putas unquam. Chriſtianum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutionem non pati,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Hierom</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epist.</hi> 1.</note>; thou art deceived (brother) thou art deceived, if thou thinkeſt that a Chriſtian at any time ſhould not ſuffer perſecution. Look backe to the infancy of the Church, when there was but one family in the world, the family of <hi>Adam;</hi> where was the Church, and you ſhall ſee <hi>Cain</hi> perſecuted <hi>Abel,</hi> and<note n="o" place="margin">Gen. 4 8. Mat. 23.35.</note> ſlew him. <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was the father<note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 4.16.</note> of the faithfull, and yet in his family, <hi>Iſmael</hi> perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Iſaack,</hi> and mocked him<note n="q" place="margin">Gal. 4 30. Gen. 21.9.</note>. <hi>Iſraell</hi> was Gods peculiar people, yet what did they ſuffer in the time of their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152100:60"/>foure hundred Yeares captivity in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> under <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> After they came out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> how were they afflicted by the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> the <hi>Moabites,</hi> the <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monites,</hi> the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> which were<note n="r" place="margin">Numb. 33.55</note> as prickes in their eyes, and thornes in their ſides? What cruell perſecution did they ſuffer under <hi>Antiochus Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> in whoſe time all were comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded<note n="ſ" place="margin">2 Macab. 6.</note> to bee put to death that would not depart from the law of their God. Deſcend downe to the time of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell; what exquiſite torments have been inflicted upon many Myriads of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, under the ten moſt bloody and grievous perſecutions, ſome being torne in peeces with wild beaſts, as <hi>Ignatius,</hi> ſome broyled on the Gridiron, as <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> ſome ſtoned to death, as<note n="t" place="margin">Euſch. Eccle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. hiſt. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>40.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Metras,</hi> others burned to death by a ſlow fire, as <hi>Iulianus</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Ibi lib. <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>39.</hi>
               </note> of <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> and the reſt put to that accurateneſſe of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that wee may ſay of them, as the Chriſtians did certifie the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152100:61"/>Pope<note n="w" place="margin">Turk. Hist. page <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> in their letters, that they did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day ſuffer that which Chriſt their King ſuffered but once, to bee dayly buffetted, ſcourged, peirced. So that what would now be accounted cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, was then accounted the Emperours clemency<note n="x" place="margin">Euſ. li. <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note>; When he commanded the right eye of the chriſtians to be plucked out, and the empty place ſeared, and the left leg to bee cut off, and the place ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and condemned them to the mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits. And to ſhew that they did ſeeke rather <hi>jugulare animos, quam corpora,</hi> to ſlay their ſoules then their bodies, they did put them to ſuch lingring tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as if they meant to kill them often. <hi>Morſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> minus poenae, quam mora mortis habet.</hi> It is a greater payne to be long a dying, then death it ſelfe: yet I read that one <hi>Peter,</hi> a Page to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, refuſing to ſacrifice at <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> was hoyſed up<note n="y" place="margin">Idem ibi. cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> on high, and his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked body ſcourged, and his fleſh rent in peeces with the laſh of the whip;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152100:61"/>and when the bones were bare, they powred vineger mixed with ſalt into the wounds, and bruiſed parts of his body, and then hee was layed on a Gridiron with a ſlow fire under, to conſume him untill hee dyed.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Quis talia fando<note n="z" place="margin">Virgil.</note>.</l>
               <l>Temperet à lacrymis?</l>
            </q>
            <p>If it bee a griefe to us ſeriouſly to conſider thoſe torments, what was it in them to endure them? Not long after the tenth perſecution ended, the the hereſy of <hi>Arrius</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Perkins on Heb. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note>, raiſed up by the divell, brought as greivous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions on the Church, as ever the <hi>Pagans</hi> did; dying and colouring the Eaſterne churches with the bloud of GODS Saints, for the ſpace of four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore yeares together. Since that time what have ſome of the <hi>Romanists</hi> ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected? With what rage and mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, fire and faggot, have they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded againſt all thoſe that profeſſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152100:62"/>not their errors: What<note n="b" place="margin">Conr. Theodor. Dieter.</note> excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications, burnings, killings, hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, they have inflicted upon the true profeſſours of the Goſpell; the maſſacre of <hi>Paris,</hi> and the death of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Chriſtians (both in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and others) do ſufficiently teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy. So that the Church did ſeeme to dwell (like the man in the Goſpell<note n="c" place="margin">Marke 5.3.</note>) among the tombs: And <hi>Christianus</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Luther loc. Com. Tit. Calamit.</note>, ſeemes to bee <hi>crucianus:</hi> A chriſtian may ſeeme to bee derived as well from Chriſts croſſe as from Chriſt.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Sanguine fundata est Eccleſia, ſanguine crevit.</l>
               <l>Sanguine ſuccrevit, ſanguine finis erit.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The Church was begun with the blood of <hi>Abel,</hi> ſtrengthened by the bloud of the Prophets, increaſed by the bloud of the Martyrs, and all<note n="e" place="margin">2 Tim. 3, 12.</note> that will live godly in Chriſt Ieſus ſhall ſuffer perſecution. If any ſhould aske
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152100:62"/>the reaſon why the Church is ſubject to the prickles of perſecution. I anſwer it is both in reſpect of the godly, and in reſpect of the wicked: An iron be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put into the fire, and heat red hot, is afterward layd on the anvill, and then every blow ſtruck upon it doth make it the fitter for uſe, but it makes the inſtruments, the Anvill, and the Hammer, the harder: ſo Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren being heat red hot (as it were) in the fire of perſecution; it makes them the better, and the more plyable to gods ſervice, but it makes the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed which are the inſtruments to bee the harder. Firſt, then, it is for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of Gods children, <hi>Candidior tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulationum aculeis efficieris,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Angelomtin loc.</note> The Church is more white and beautifull by the prickles of perſecution. The Church is compared to the Moone<note n="g" place="margin">Sol. Song. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note>: <hi>Eccleſia ſicut luna defectus habet, &amp; ortus fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentes, ſed defectibus ſuis crevit, &amp; his meruit ampliari, dum perſecutionibus
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152100:63"/>minuitur, &amp; martyrio coronatur,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Hexam. li. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note>; The Church (like the Moone) hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ifings and ſettings, fulls and waynes, but ſhee increaſeth by her defects, and deſerves to be aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, while ſhee is leſſened by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution and crowned with Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. We cannot bee crowned except wee fight, neither can wee triumph except wee have got the victory; when we fight and conquer, then may tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheys bee ſet up. In the ſhop of a Ieweller, the Iewells would not bee ſo beautifull, if there were no iron in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumens to furbiſh them. <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple had never been ſo glorious, if there had been no craggy ſtones to build it: ſo Gods children would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ſo beautifull in themſelves, nor ſo glorious in the fight of God, if they had no perſecution to try them. When we ſit by the waters of <hi>Babylon,</hi> then wee remember thee<note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 137.1.</note>, O <hi>Sion.</hi> As the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſayes of himſelfe<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 119 17.</note>, It
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152100:63"/>is good for me that I have been afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; ſo may many a member of the Church ſay, it is good for mee that I have been perſecuted Man (ſaith one<note n="l" place="margin">Clem Alexand</note>) is like unto a vine; now a vine (as hee there ſpeakes, and we here know) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be pruned, it will ſtreight way grow wilde: ſo man, if hee have no perſecution, no croſſe layd upon him, hee will bee ready to forget himſelfe, and to ſpurne againſt his maker. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution then is like the wind, which doth cleanſe the good grayne though it blow cold; like the fire which doth purify the good gold, though it burne hot: for the godly are bettered by it, their knowledge is ſounder then it was, their faith ſtronger, their humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity lower, their goodnes in generall is greater, towards GOD, towards their neighbours, and towards them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. And as it is for the benefit of Gods children, and tends to their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; ſo it proceeds from the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152100:64"/>of the wicked, and ends in their deſtruction. <hi>Iniquitatis filii, cum claro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum hominum virtutem repraehenſionem quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dammodo ſuae pravitatis existimant, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luti immanes quaedam ferae crudeliter ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Cyrill</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> Gen. <hi>lib.</hi> 10.</note>; The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath, when they ſee the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of good men reprove their vices, they rage like wilde beaſts: for when by their works of light the works of darknes are reproved, they caſt the darts of envy and malice againſt them, which doe oftentimes returne back on their owne pates. The fire of martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome<note n="n" place="margin">S. <hi>Auguſtin.</hi>
               </note>, which doth purify the godly, doth damnify the wicked, the one it doth enrich with eternall happines, the other it ſhall conſume to duſt and aſhes. <hi>Aſhur</hi> is ſaid to bee the rod of Gods anger<note n="o" place="margin">Eſay 10.5.</note> and wicked men are but the rods of his wrath, with which though he doth ſometimes chaſtice his children (and ſuffer them to bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted) yet at length hee will burne
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152100:64"/>the rodds. But ſome may object, and ſay, that in thoſe dangerous times of the primitive Church, the Church might properly be ſaid to bee <hi>the red, Roſe of Sharon;</hi> When a man might pay deare for Chriſt, as Chriſt payd for him, even his life; it being (then) almoſt impoſſible to follow Chriſt without Martyrdome. But now (thanks bee to God) there is no ſuch danger, no <hi>Chriſtianus ad Leones?</hi> let the Chriſtians bee caſt into the Lions den, no pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling before Magiſtrates, but every one may practiſe chriſtianity, as well as profeſſe it without danger; nay it is dangerous indeede to every one that doth not profeſſe and practiſe it (in our Kingdome) and God continue it ſo long as the Sun and Moone endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſo that the Church may now ſeeme to bee free from the rednes, and prickles of perſecution. To this anſwere is made<note n="p" place="margin">Chryſ. Theoph apud Coſma in <hi>2 Tim. 3.12</hi>
               </note>, that to ſuffer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution is taken not onely for that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152100:65"/>which Gods children ſuffer from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen enemies, but for that griefe and ſorrow which they ſuffer in their owne bowells. <hi>Patiuntur hanc perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem non in corporibus, ſed in cordibus,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Austin,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">De Civitat dei li. <hi>18.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> they ſuffer this perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not outwardly in their bodyes, but inwardly in their ſoules. And there is a perſecution of the tongue, as well as a perſecution of the hand. The Scripture prompts me to it, where it ſayes<note n="r" place="margin">Gal 4.21.</note> 
               <hi>Iſmael</hi> perſecuted <hi>Iſaac,</hi> when hee<note n="ſ" place="margin">Gen. 21.9.</note> mocked him. So that there is diſguiſed as well as open perſecution,<note n="t" place="margin">Wiſſons Chriſt. Diction.</note> by word as well as by Sword, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit as well as violence, from falſe bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren as well as from profeſſed ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. And this kind of perſecution I cannot ſay that our Church is free from; for that Schiſmaticall brood that whips it in their words, and ſcourgeth it in their Pamphlets writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten againſt the government and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of the Church, what doe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152100:65"/>they elſe but (as much as in them lyes) v kill the Prophets,<note n="u" place="margin">Mat 23.37.</note> and ſtone them that are ſent them. And who ſo pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently beare<note n="w" place="margin">
                  <hi>Doctor</hi> Boys expoſit of the <hi>Goſpell</hi> on <hi>S.</hi> Steph. day.</note> thoſe wrongs, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thoſe dilapidations in their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dits, what are they elſe but <hi>Stephens,</hi> meere Martyrs. And this kind of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution muſt the Church never looke to bee free from. Though ſhee may ſometimes bee free from ſtripes and ſtrokes, yet ſhee is never free from mocks and ſcoffs; though ſhee may bee free from deaths and impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, yet never from raylings and revilings; though ſhee may bee free from murtherings, yet not from mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings, and ſo never free from the pricks of ſecret perſecution. By this wee may partly ſee whether wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Church or no. Wee live in the latter dayes, wherein many that ſhould countenance Religion do contemne it, being like unto the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groes<note n="x" place="margin">Heylens G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ogr.</note> that paint the Divell white, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152100:66"/>the Angels black, becauſe they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are ſo. Doſt thou then like the weather-cock turne thy ſelfe by their wind, and conforme thy ſelfe to them, for feare of loſing a favour, or get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a frowne? thou art not a true mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church. Againe, we live in a ſcoffing age, wherein true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are accounted by many, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> was<note n="y" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.13.</note>, <hi>the filth of the World, and the off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouring of all things.</hi> Art thou aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be religious, becauſe thou art af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayd to be ſcoft at? Art thou affraid to be ſlaundered, as the Lords Prieſts<note n="z" place="margin">1 Sam. 22.</note> were by malicious <hi>Doeg?</hi> Art thou af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to be rayled at, as <hi>David</hi> was<note n="a" place="margin">2 Sam. 16.7</note> by freviling <hi>Shimei?</hi> Art thou affrayd to ſuffer affliction with the people of God? How then wouldſt thou bee contented to be ſtoned<note n="b" place="margin">Acts 7.59.</note> with <hi>Steven?</hi> to bee caſt into the fiery Furnace<note n="c" place="margin">Dan. 3.23.</note>, with the three children, or into the Lions Den with<note n="d" place="margin">Dan. 6.16.</note> 
               <hi>Daniel?</hi> to have thy tongue cut out, thy skin pulled
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152100:66"/>of<note n="e" place="margin">2 Maccab. 7.</note> thy head, and bee fryed in a Pan, as the Mother and her ſeven ſonnes? doe thoſe ſmall skirmiſhes make thee afraid, and thinkeſt thou thou could<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt endure the heat of the battayle? Queſtionles if thoſe ſmall blaſts make thy ſoule to totter, why then the ſtorme of perſecution will plucke thee up by the roots. Wee ſtand betweene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity and adverſity, as <hi>Goliah</hi> did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the two troopes<note n="f" place="margin">1 Sam. 17.10</note>, and wiſh that wee had a man to fight withall. But if the leaſt ſtorme ariſe, the hearts of many fayle. So that as <hi>Ioſephs</hi> bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren ſayd unto their Father, <hi>Vide an filii tui tunica ſit, an non?</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Gen.</note> ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bee thy ſons coat or no? ſo may I ſay to the Church concerning any of her members, <hi>Vide an ſit filii tui tunica, an non?</hi> if hee bee free from all manner of perſecution and trouble, it is a ſigne hee is a baſtard and no Son: but if his coat be dyed in bloud, if he can ſhew the right colour, it is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152100:67"/>a ſigne that hee doth belong to the <hi>red Roſe of Sharon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the ſweetnes of the <hi>Roſe</hi> repreſents the Churches ſweet converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon earth, and that both in words and works. The ſweetnes of the lips in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth learning, ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Prov. 16.21.</note>; good words are ſweet words, &amp; the Church and the members thereof muſt ſpeake them, and not unſavoury ſpeech. We are ſtrangers and pilgrims in this life, for here<note n="i" place="margin">Heb. 13.14.</note> we have no abiding place, but we ſeeke one to come. Now ſtrangers and pilgrims are knowne by their tongues, for he that<note n="k" place="margin">John 3.31.</note> is of the earth, ſpeaketh of the earth: Earth is at their hearts, and their breathes ſmell of it. But the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of light (which are not ſo wiſe as the children of this generation<note n="l" place="margin">Luke 16.8.</note>) concerning the things of this World are dumbe: they know not the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the lyar<note n="m" place="margin">Eph. 4.25.</note>, but their tongues are tipt with truth. They are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the language of the black mouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152100:67"/>ſwearer, but his communication<note n="n" place="margin">Mat 5.37.</note> is <hi>yea, yea,</hi> and <hi>nay, nay,</hi> in a word, hee knowes not the language of <hi>Babel,</hi> but ſpeakes the language of <hi>Canaan.</hi> Now there is the ſweetnes of Honey in godly diſcourſes, but the bitternes of Gall and Worm-wood in wicked words, and although wicked men may (happily) thinke that they find ſweetnes in them, yet they are like the Bee, though they bee Honey in the mouth, yet they have a ſting in the tayle. They are like S. <hi>Iohns</hi> booke<note n="o" place="margin">Rev. 10.10.</note>, though in the mouth they bee ſweet as Honey, yet in the belly they are bitter, for what <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid of a whoriſh wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man<note n="p" place="margin">Prov. 5.4.</note>, ſo may I ſay of them, though in the mouth it be ſweet as an hony comb, yet their end is bitter as Worm-wood.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Church muſt alſo ſhew ſweetnes in her works. <hi>Ad prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicationem novae gratiae, ſecuta est novi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas vitae, in his qui crediderunt qui con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſationem ſuam inter gentes habentes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152100:68"/>Chriſti erant bonus odor in om nilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">In Cantic. Ser. <hi>60.</hi>
               </note> Newnes of life did follow the preaching of the new grace of the Goſpell, in them which did beleeve, who having their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation honeſt among the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> were a ſweet favour unto Chriſt in every place. For, <hi>Plantae quae benè olent bonam famam &amp; nomen pollicentur</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Hier: Card Sinineſ. Somni li. <hi>1.</hi> cap <hi>30.</hi>
               </note>, thoſe Flowers that ſmell ſweetly do ſignify a good name and report. <hi>Odor bonus, eſt nomen bonum, &amp; hoc de bono opere, tanquam de flore odor, procedit,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Bern.</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Vbi prius</note> A ſweet ſmell is a good report, which proceedes from good workes, even as ſweetnes doth from the Flower. The good works of the godly caſt a ſweet ſmell even to them that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. <hi>Bona quidem per ſe ſunt aromata virtutum, &amp; per ſe redolere videntur, ſed cumulatiore gratia flagrant, cum de uncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one ſpiritus, ſuavitatis afperguntur odo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Gilleber in Cantic. Ser. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note>, The ſpices of vertues are good, and ſmell ſweet in themſelves (if in the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152100:68"/>heathen) but they give the more fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant ſmell, when they are ſprinkled with the odor of ſweetnes by the anoynting of the ſpirit (in the godly) good works are an odour of a ſweet ſmell unto men, and a Sacrifice ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable, well pleaſing unto God, as the Apoſtle tells the <hi>Philippians</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Phil. 4 18.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their charity. The Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">Hoſ. 14.7.</note>, ſpeaking of the Church ſayes, it ſhall grow as the Vine, the ſent thereof ſhall bee as the Wine of <hi>Leba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non.</hi> It is written<note n="x" place="margin">Daneus from Pliny lib. <hi>14.7.</hi>
               </note> of ſome Vines that in the time of their floriſhing, they ſend forth ſo ſweet a ſmell, that not onely the Vine-yards themſelves, but the Countrey round about, is refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the ſweet ſavour thereof, ſo that if any Serpents bee neere, they are driven away by the ſweet ſmell of the Vines; ſo the converſation of the godly is no leſſe fragrant, not only in themſelves, but alſo to all that are round about. A good name is better
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152100:69"/>then precious oyntment<note n="y" place="margin">Eccles 7.1.</note>. And the godly have their converſation ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt among the <hi>Gentiles</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">1 Pet 2.12.</note>, that they may by their good workes which they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, glorify GOD in the day of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation. And their ſweet converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth drive away Serpents; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we expound Serpents, as S. <hi>Austin</hi> doth<note n="a" place="margin">In Pſal. 42.</note>, <hi>Serpentes vitia tua ſunt,</hi> The Serpents are thy ſins; then their works of light expell thoſe workes of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: or elſe as S. <hi>Bern.</hi> doth<note n="b" place="margin">De Paſſ. Dom cap <hi>45.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>Quid melius per Serpentes, quam diabolicas ſuggeſtiones accipiamus?</hi> What is better meant by Serpents, then the ſuggeſtions of Satan, which doe ſecretly creepe into the minds of men; then if wee looke upon that braſen Serpent Chriſt Ieſus, which was lifted up upon the Croſſe, by the eye of a true and lively Faith working by love, and ſending forth the ſweet ſavour of good works, we ſhall bee<note n="c" place="margin">Ephe 6.16.</note> able to quench all the fiery darts of the wicked. The ſmell
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152100:69"/>of the Churches oyntments<note n="d" place="margin">Cant. 4.10, 11.</note> (that is, her graces) is better then all ſpices, and the ſmell of her garments, is like the ſmell of <hi>Lebanon.</hi> But when <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſmelled the ſavour of <hi>Iacobs</hi> garments, they were nor his owne, for<note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 27.15.</note> 
               <hi>Rebeccah</hi> tooke goodly rayment of her elder Son <hi>Eſau,</hi> and put them on <hi>Iacob.</hi> As hee was cloathed with the rayment of his elder brother which gave ſuch a ſweet ſmell: ſo the Church is cloathed, not with the garment of her owne right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eouſnes, but ſhee puts on the glorious robe of her elder brother CHRIST IESVS, by which ſhe is made the ſweet <hi>Roſe of Sharon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, as the <hi>Roſe</hi> is dead in winter, but ſhoots forth againe at the Spring: ſo though the members of the Church ly a long time in the grave, yet at the Spring of the reſurrection they ſhal riſe againe. As long as the root is quick, the branches will not die, but flouriſh. Chriſt is the root<note n="f" place="margin">Rev. 5.5. &amp; 22.11.</note>, we are the branches<note n="g" place="margin">John 15.5.</note>, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152100:70"/>our root did not rot in the ground, but roſe from the grave, to certify us, the branches, of the reſurrection. As long as the head is above the water, the body cannot bee drowned. Chriſt is<note n="h" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.3. Eph. 5.23.</note> the head, wee are<note n="i" place="margin">1 Cor. 12.27.</note> the body; but Chriſt our head is riſen from the dead, and his members, the Church, ſhall aſſuredly riſe from death to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of life. As Chriſt<note n="k" place="margin">Church Hom. of the Reſurrection.</note> dyed not for himſelfe, no more did hee riſe againe for himſelfe, but for us. <hi>Quia tu Redemptor noſter ſuſcepit mortem, ne mori timeremus; ita ostendit reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem, ut nos reſurgere poſſe confideremus:</hi> for as our Redeemer dyed that wee ſhould not be afrayd of death; ſo he roſe againe, that we may bee ſure of our Reſurrection unto life. GODS Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with his Church<note n="l" place="margin">Jerem. 31.33.</note>, I will be their GOD, and they ſhall be my people,<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pe kins</hi> on the Creed.</note> is an everlaſting covenant to laſt for ever; but if God ſhould leave his people in the grave for ever, how could they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152100:70"/>bee called the people of GOD? for<note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 22.31.</note> for GOD is not the GOD of the dead, but of the living, and therefore ſeeing Gods Covenant is everlaſting to all, the Faithfull muſt riſe from the dead, that God may alwayes bee ſaid to bee their God, and the godly be alwayes ſaid to be his people. It is an eſpeciall part of Gods glory to ſhew forth his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy on the godly, and his Iuſtice on the wicked, to render<note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 2.6.</note> to every man according to his deeds. But here in this life<note n="p" place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.2.</note> all things come alike to all, to the righteous, and to the wicked. and therefore there muſt bee a reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the dead, that the godly may have a reward from his mercy; and the wicked from his juſtice. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectio quidem communis est, &amp; ante tribunal Christi neceſſe eſt in corpore justos ſtare &amp; impios, Dei hoc dictante juſtitia, ut pietas &amp; impietas in operatoribus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitis ſtipendiis donarentur</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">De R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſurrec. Chriſti.</note>. The reſurrection (indeed)
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152100:71"/>is common, and it is neceſſary that all, both good and bad, ſtand before the tribunall of Chriſt, that both piety and impiety might receive a due wages in the workers thereof; <hi>Et qui finem habere contempſerunt in malis, infinita clauderentur ultione in poenis &amp; qui glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riati ſunt in cruce, cum crucifixo regnantes, beatae fierent perennitatis participes;</hi> And that they which refuſed to have an end in evill, might bee ſhut up in payne without end; and they which glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Croſſe, might reigne with him that was crucified, and bee par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of bleſſed everlaſtingnes. For God, as hee is <hi>principium effectivum in creatione, refectivum in redemptione,</hi> ſo hee is <hi>principium perfectivum in retribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh</hi> de Comb. Comp. Theol. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note>, as hee is the efficient cauſe in the creation, the reficient in the redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo he is the perficient in the retri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution. Why ſhould any <hi>Epicure,</hi> or <hi>Atheist</hi> deny, that the omnipotent and everlaſting God ſhould bee able to raiſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152100:71"/>mens bodies out of the duſt, when experience tells us, that miſerable and impotent men, can by art make the curious workmanſhip of glaſſe? <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus eſt Deo reparare quod erat, quam feciſſe quod non erat</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">S. <hi>Gregor.</hi>
               </note>; It is a leſſe matter to reſtore that which was, than to make that which was not. And therefore though the members of the Church ſhould have their bodies torne in pieces by tyrants, or conſumed to aſhes by fire, or rent by wilde beaſts, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by Wormes or Fiſhes, yet they doe but reſt a while in the earth; for at the Reſurrection they ſhall bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, when they ſhall riſe from their graves, as the <hi>Roſe</hi> (in the Spring) from the ground, for therein the Church reſembles the ſpringing <hi>Roſe of Sharon.</hi> And ſo I come to the limitation of this attribute (of <hi>Sharon.</hi>)</p>
            <p>The fruitfulnes of <hi>Sharon</hi> ſhewes, that though the Church before Chriſt were barren like <hi>Sarah,</hi> or <hi>Rachel,</hi> yet
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152100:72"/>by him it is made as fruitfull as <hi>Leah.</hi> But I promiſed to proceed in the ſame method that I did before, and therefore (the word <hi>Sharon</hi> ſignifying any Field) I muſt ſhew you that the Church reſembles the <hi>Roſe of the common Field</hi> in three reſpects.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Flowers of the Field grow by the providence of God without the helpe of man. <hi>Campus ex ſemetipſo flores producit, abſque omni humanae dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentiae adjutorio</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">In loc. Ser. <hi>4.7.</hi>
               </note>: The Field produceth her flowers without the induſtry of man. So the Church is not planted by mans induſtry, but by the providence of God. The Trees<note n="n" place="margin">Doctor <hi>Dove</hi> on Cant. 4.12.</note> grow not in it naturally as the Trees of the Forreſt, which beare no Fruit: but they are planted by the labour and induſtry of the husbandman, as the fig-Tree. God planteth all that are in the Vine-yard of his Church, as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſaith<note n="w" place="margin">Mat. 15.13.</note> 
               <hi>Every plant which my hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father hath not planted ſhall be rooted
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152100:72"/>up.</hi> It is he that brings forth<hi rend="sup">g</hi> 
               <hi>his vine-yard out of Egypt,</hi> &amp; plants it too.<note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 80.8.</note> The Church is a Vine-yard, God is the husbandman that plants and keepes it, it is watered by the word, dreſſed by the Miniſters, refreſhed by the comfortable Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine of the Goſpell. And here is a difference<note n="y" place="margin">Doctor <hi>Hall Ser. on</hi> I ſay 5.4.</note>: betweene <hi>Solomons</hi> Vine-yard and his that is greater then <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Mat. 12.42.</note>, <hi>Solomon</hi> let out his Vine-yard<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sol. Song.</hi> 8.11.</note> to keepers, but Chriſt keepes his in his owne hand, hee uſeth the help of men ſometimes, but as tooles rather then agents, hee works by them, they cannot worke but by him. And as it is planted by him, ſo is it watered by him. As Promotion (ſo grace) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal 75 7.</note> neither from the Eaſt, nor yet from the Weſt, but from God. What the Apoſtle ſaith<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8.</note> of ſalvation, may bee ſaid of all grace, It is not of our ſelves, leſt any men ſhould boaſt. We have no more power of our ſelves, to work grace in our ſelves, then theſe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152100:73"/>inferiour bodies have power to give light, when the light of the Sunne is abſent. <hi>Adams</hi> ability was loſt by his fall, now <hi>Sampſons</hi> locks are cut off, and therefore we may bee carried whither our leader (the divell) will, ſince wee ſuffered that <hi>Dalilah,</hi> ſinne, to ſteale away our ſtrength from us. <hi>Adam per malum velle, perdidit bonum poſſe,</hi> by willing that which is evill, hee loſt his ability to performe that that is good; and ſince him every mothers ſon may bee called, as the wife of <hi>Phinehas</hi> named her child,<note n="d" place="margin">1 Sam 4.21.</note> 
               <hi>Ichabod,</hi> for in him this glory departed from us. GOD now worketh in us<note n="e" place="margin">Phil. 2.13.</note> both the will and the deed. <hi>Ipſe aſpirando nos praevenit ut ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limus quod adjuvando ſubſequitur, ne inaniter velimus,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Gregory</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">In Ezek. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Hom.</hi> 9.</note>; Hee by his preventing grace makes us to will that which by his aſſiſting grace he makes us to performe. The ſap and juice that is in the <hi>Roſe-Tree</hi> proceeds from the root, and the grace that is in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152100:73"/>the members of the Church (whether it be <hi>gratia infuſa, effuſa,</hi> or <hi>diffuſa,</hi> in thought, word or worke) doth proceed from God the Fountaine of grace. <hi>Non est gratia ullo modo, niſi ſit gratuita omni modo:</hi> it is not grace except in bee given <hi>gratis.</hi> So that the planting of the members in the Church and the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering them for their growth, being planted, proceeds not from themſelves but from God; for therein the Church reſembles the <hi>Roſe</hi> of the common Field.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the <hi>Roſe</hi> of the Field is not incloſed to a few, as the garden <hi>Roſe</hi> is, but lyes open to all; ſo the Church is not incloſed in ſome narrow nooke or corner, but is ſpread through the World, and lyes open to receive all. Before Chriſt, <hi>Iſrael</hi> was Gods peculiar people, the nation that hee had choſen to ſet his name there, to them hee gave his word, with them hee made his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and ſhewed them the preſence
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152100:74"/>of his god-head. He dealt not ſo with other nations, neither had<note n="g" place="margin">Pſalme 147.20.</note> the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the knowledge of his waies. So that then <hi>Iacob</hi> was the man that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vayled with God, and his poſterity, the onely <hi>Iſrael</hi> that ſaw him. He ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered other nations to ſit in darknes, and in the ſhadow of death. Then <hi>Iſrael</hi> was<note n="h" place="margin">Calv. Inſtit.</note> the Lords Son that was his dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, others were ſtrangers. <hi>Iſrael</hi> was received into his care and protection, others were left to their owne blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: <hi>Iſrael</hi> was honoured with the preſence of God, others were excluded from coming nigh him, in a word there was a generall darknes over all the Land of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> among the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles:</hi> but in the Land of <hi>Goſhen</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Exod. 10.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> there was light. But ſince Chriſt the mercy of God was no longer incloſed within the narrow confines of <hi>Iewry,</hi> but the glorious light of the Goſpell ſhined through the World. Before Chriſt the Church was
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152100:74"/>a garden incloſed,<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sol. Song.</hi> 4.12.</note> a ſpring ſhut up, a Fountaine ſealed, but now ſhe is the <hi>Roſe of the common Feild.</hi> The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven, is likened unto a man,<note n="l" place="margin">Mat 13.24.</note> which ſowed good ſeed in his Field. The Church is the Field, the ſeed is the word, and the Goſpell ſhall be preached through the World<note n="m" place="margin">Mat 26.13.</note>. And to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Church is called Catholique <hi>Catholica, id est, per totum orbem diffuſa,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>August.</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 170. <hi>&amp;</hi> in Pſ. 56.</note> becauſe it is ſpread through the World. And ſo the Epiſtles of S. <hi>Iames,</hi> S. <hi>Peter,</hi> S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> and S. <hi>Iude,</hi> are called <hi>Catholique,</hi> becauſe<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Willſons</hi> Chriſt. Dictio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary.</note>, they are written not to a particuler perſon, as to <hi>Timothy,</hi> &amp;c. or to a particular Church as to the <hi>Romans,</hi> &amp;c. but either to all the <hi>Iewes</hi> every where, or to all the Chriſtians in the World. And to this purpoſe alſo the Apoſtle calls<note n="p" place="margin">Heb 12.22.</note>, the Church <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Conventus vniverſalis,</hi> the generall aſſembly, to ſhew the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality of it. The Apoſtle S. <hi>Peter</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes<note n="g" place="margin">Acts 10.34.</note>. Of a truth that God is no reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecter
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152100:75"/>of perſons, but in every nation, hee that feareth him, and worketh righteouſnes, is accepted with him. Though the Church bee but one, yet it lyes open to all that will come unto it. <hi>Vnus est Chriſtus, per quem omnis gens omniſque lingua fide &amp; confeſsione unita est</hi> ſaith <hi>Ignatius</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Apud Amand. Polan.</note>, there is but one Chriſt (and one Church) by whom (and in whom) all nations, and tongues are knit together. <hi>Quid enim est Eccleſia ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ud, quam congregatio fidelium in unitate fidei advnita</hi> ſaith <hi>Oecolampadius</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Annotat in Chryſit.</note> What elſe is the Church of God, but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of faithfull people (ſpread through the World) knit together in the vnity of faith: the Church is ſpread every where through the World; and admits any perſons in the World into her boſome. And therefore the Church is not to bee tyed to <hi>Rome,</hi> or any one particuler place, <hi>Rome</hi> may with no better reaſon be ſayd to bee the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church, then the head may bee
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152100:75"/>ſayd to be the whole body: for if it bee a true Church, yet it is but a part of the Church Catholique, and not the whole. And to ſay the Catholique Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is all one, as if I ſhould ſay the catholique Church of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> or of <hi>London,</hi> or a particular univerſall Church, which how harſh it ſounds the moſt ſimple may eaſily underſtand. After this I beheld ſaith S. <hi>Iohn</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Rev. 7.9.</note>, <hi>and loe, a great multitude which no man could num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of all nations, and kindred, and people, and tongues, ſtood before the Throne, and before the Lambe, cloathed with white Robes, and palmes in their hands.</hi> The Church is collected out of all nations. <hi>Aceipit Eccleſia omni tempore volentes credere nemini prorſus occludit ſe huc festin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anti, ſed liberum &amp; licitum eſt volentibus quolibet tempore, nullo impediente, ad lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem veritatis adduci</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Cyrill</hi> v.<note n="u" place="margin">In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l. lib. <hi>5</hi> cap. <hi>60.</hi>
               </note> The Church receaveth all that will beleeve at all times, ſhee is ſhut to none that come unto her, but it is free and lawfull
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152100:76"/>to all that will (there is none to hinder them) to come to the knowledge of the truth. And therefore if thou haſt no benefit by this <hi>Roſe,</hi> if thou art no member of the Church blame thy ſelfe, for ſhee is not the incloſed <hi>Roſe</hi> of the Garden, but the <hi>Roſe</hi> of the common Field.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the <hi>Roſe</hi> of the Field is for profit, as well as pleaſure, and is health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in many medicines: ſo the Church is profitable, and healthfull to her members. Shee reſtores health to her members by monitions and admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſtrengthning them that are ſound by wholeſome Doctrine, and reſtoring them that are ſicke by good diſcipline. But if any member be paſt cure then.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note n="w" place="margin">Ovid Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morph.</note> Immedicabile vulnus</l>
               <l>Enſe redendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, ne pars ſincera trahatur.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Then ſhee cuts it off by the ſpirituall ſword of Excommunication. Thoſe that are in the barren Wildernes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152100:76"/>the pale of the Church are miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, there is <hi>mors in olla,</hi> death is in their pot, but thoſe that are within the pale of the Church in that fruitfull Field, are happy, there is health in her boſome. The Church of God is the Houſe of God<note n="x" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.15.</note>, the Pillar and ground of truth. And ſhee is very profitable unto her members, <hi>Extra Eccleſiam nulla ſalus,</hi> is a common ſaying among the fathers, without the Church there is no ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Without the Church they cannot attayne unto the right of adoption, whereby they that live faithfully, are made actually the children of GOD. They that continue in the Ship of the Church are ſecure<note n="y" place="margin">Doctor <hi>Boys</hi>
               </note>, though the Sea make a noyſe, and ſtormes ariſe, but hee that utterly forſakes the Ship of the Church, and ſwims either in the cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boate of hereſies, or upon the windy bladders of his owne conceipt, ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver touch the land of the living. Thoſe that are out of the, Church have not the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152100:77"/>communion and intereſt of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers with the head, and being no part of his body how can they lay claime to his benefits? or challenge right to the Kingdome of heaven. And to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe heaven is called<note n="z" place="margin">Acts. 26.18.</note> the inheritance of them which are ſanctifyed by faith in CHRIST.</p>
            <p>Nothing now remaines to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of at this time, but onely that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one fill his pitcher with this water, and carry it home for his owne uſe; which that wee may doe; I ſhall briefly apply. Firſt, in that the Church is the red <hi>Roſe</hi> by perſecution, every one ſhould learne patience in his affliction. Remember the ſufferings of Chriſt, wee doe but ſup of that Cup which hee dranke quite off. <hi>Nihil eſt quod non aequanimiter tolleretur, ſi paſsio Chriſti in memoriam revocetur.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">St. <hi>Gregory.</hi>
               </note> There is no affliction ſo great, no croſſe ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous that will not eaſily be borne by us, if wee doe rememberthe ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152100:77"/>of Chriſt: And therefore <hi>Vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa pro eo ſustine, qui prius pro te Majora ſuſtinuit</hi> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">de Reſurrec. Dom.</note> ſuffer ſome perſecution for his ſake, that ſuffered more for thine. Secondly, let us labour for our Renovation that our newnes of life may ſend forth a ſweet ſavour in our converſation. Thirdly, in that the Church and the members thereof ſhall riſe from the dead: it affords matter of our conſolation: For ſo the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes<note n="c" place="margin">Pſa. 16 9 10</note> 
               <hi>Therefore my heart is glad, and my glory rejoyceth, my fleſh alſo ſhall rest in hope: for thou wilt not leave my ſoule in hell,</hi> neither <hi>wilt thou ſuffer thy holy one to ſee corruption.</hi> Fourthly, ſeeing the Church is of Gods owne planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, let us looke to our fructification. Our Saviour putteth forth the parable of the Figge tree to us<note n="d" place="margin">Luke 13.6.</note> 
               <hi>A certaine man had a Figge Tree in his Vineyard, and hee came and ſought fruit thereon three Yeares:</hi> Every one of us is a Tree planted in the Vineyard of the Church: God
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152100:78"/>hath expected fruit of us three Yeares, in generall of the whole Kingdome, under the Raignes of our moſt gracious Soveraignes, Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi>Iames,</hi> and King <hi>Charles;</hi> in particular of every private perſons, the three ages of mans life, infancy, youth, old age: let not us give him the bark of an outward profeſſion onely, nor the leaves of good works, but the fruit of good workes. Laſtly, ſeeing the Church is open to all commers, let every one of us labour to be of that corporation, that we may bee partakers of all the benefits that accrew thereby, and that being members of the Church militant, we may reigne with the Church triumphant. <hi>Which God grant unto us all for Ieſus Christs ſake. To whom with the Father and the holy Ghoſt, three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and one God, be al ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and praiſe, now and for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:152100:78"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To</hi> The Right Worſhipfull, his much Honoured friend THOMAS PARKS, <hi>Eſquier.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F <hi>Eliſha</hi> were at a ſtand, when hee conſidered what the good <hi>Shuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite</hi> had done for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im, that hee aſkes<note n="a" place="margin">2 Kings 4.13.</note>. What to bee done againe for her? sAnd <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> for <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decay,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:152100:79"/>when hee had recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a good turne from him that hee ſaies<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſther.</hi> 6.3.</note>, What hath beene done to him for this? How much more maie I ſaie of you, you have been beneficiall to mee from my Youth, what du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and ſervice ſhall J re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to you againe? J confeſſe that if there bee anie thing in theſe my weake labours that maie deſerue acceptance, you maie juſtlie challenge it as your owne, Without whoſe bountie I had not lived in the <hi>Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity,</hi> nor attained to that ſmall meaſure of knowledge that J have. And therefore (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to doe nothing elſe)
<pb facs="tcp:152100:79"/>J commit this <hi>Sermon</hi> to your Patronage and protection, and your ſelfe, your fruitfull Vine, and Olive branches to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of the <hi>Almighty,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring him to give you the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of his Right hand, and of his left, to fill you with the bleſſing of grace heere, and of glorie hereafter.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, to be commanded in Chriſt Jeſus WILLIAM PARKES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="lecture">
            <pb facs="tcp:152100:80"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152100:80"/>
            <head>THE ROSE AND LILY.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>SOLOMONS SONG. 2.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>J am the <hi>Roſe</hi> of Sharon, and the <hi>Lily</hi> of the vallyes.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat S. <hi>Ierome</hi> ſayes<note n="a" place="margin">Ad Paulin.</note> of the Catholique Epiſtles, of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> S. <hi>James,</hi> S. <hi>John,</hi> and S. <hi>Jude. Breves eſſe pariter &amp; longas,</hi> that they are both ſhort and long, ſo may I ſay of this <hi>Text,</hi> it is ſhort in words, but long in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152100:81"/>matter. And what S. <hi>Austin</hi> ſayes<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Praefat</hi> in Pſal. 87.</note>, of the foureſcore and ſeaventh <hi>Pſalme. Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis est numero verborum, magnus pondere ſententiarum,</hi> that it is ſhort in regard of the number of the words, long in reſpect of the weightines of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: ſo may I ſay of this <hi>Text,</hi> it is a ſhort ſentence, but full of ſence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning matter for (almoſt) as many Sermons as it conteynes words. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but five words in the <hi>Originall,</hi> yet is the ſubject of foure Sermons. Three of them have been delivered formerly, and now the fourth, (the ſame aſſiſtance ſtrengthing, and the ſame patience expecting) is to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, in ſhewing you wherein the Church reſembles <hi>the Lily of the Valleys.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, the <hi>Lily</hi> is open toward hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven but cloſe and ſhut toward earth, ſo the members of the Church muſt have their affections open on things above.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152100:81"/>
Secondly, the leaves of the <hi>Lily</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend outwards and bend downwards, a fit embleme of the Churches cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the <hi>Lily</hi> is white, which ſignifies the Churches innocency.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the <hi>Lily</hi> growes among Thornes, and in the Church there is a commixtion of good and bad, in theſe reſpects the Church (alſo) reſembles <hi>the Lily of the Valleyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, the Flower of the <hi>Lily</hi> is lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upward, and ſpreades toward heaven, but toward the earth it is cloſe, and ſhut, whence the Church and the members thereof, may learne a <hi>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum corda,</hi> to lift up their hearts and to open them towards heaven, but to keepe them cloſe ſhut toward earth, and earthly things. Wee read in the Law<note n="c" place="margin">Lev. 11 42.</note>, That thoſe creatures, which crept on their bellyes, were uncleane, ſo under the Goſpell, thoſe men that have their bellies, their affections, creep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152100:82"/>on the earth are uncleane. <hi>Si de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectat te mundus, ſemper vis eſſe immun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, ſi autem non te delectat mundus, jam tu es mundus</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">In John Tr. 36.</note>, If the World delight thee, then thou art ſtill a worldling, and uncleane, but if the World delight thee not, then art thou choſen out of the World, and art cleane. Man is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>Greeke,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> from looking upward, his name may put him in mind of his nature, and duty, to looke upward, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template on heavenly things. And whereas all other creatures looke downward toward the earth the place from whence they were taken.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Os homini ſublime dedit, coelumque Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere</l>
               <l>Iuſsit, &amp; erectos ad ſidera tallere vultus.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Saith the <hi>Poet</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ovid Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morph. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> man hath his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance erected toward heaven, to looke up to that place to which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152100:82"/>hee ſhould aſpire. God made not<note n="f" place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.29. and 15.</note> man crooked (but upright) for who can ſtreighten that which hee hath made crooked? but man boweth downe himſelfe by his owne inventions, and makes himſelfe like that woman in the Goſpell<note n="g" place="margin">Inke. 13.11.</note>, which was ſo bowed together that ſhee could in no wiſe lift up her ſelfe. But as the eye is placed in the head to looke upward, ſo is the heart in the body open to contemplate on heavenly things: For if you looke into an Anatomy, you ſhall ſee that the heart is broad above and narrow be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, ſignifying it ſhould bee open toward Heaven but contracted toward the things of this life. The windowes of our ſpirituall temples, our bodyes muſt be built like the windowes<note n="h" place="margin">1 King. 6 4.</note> of <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> broad without, toward Heaven, and narrow within: But ſuch is the nature and diſpoſition of the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> that <hi>Maryes</hi> choyce cannot content them,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152100:83"/>that <hi>Vnum neceſſarium,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Luk. 10.40 42.</note> that one thing that is needfull, to ſit and heare Chriſt and to be buſied about heavenly things, but with <hi>Martha</hi> wee are too much cumbred with earthly affaires: we do not firſt<note n="k" place="margin">Mat. 6.3.</note> ſeeke the kingdome of God and the righteouſneſſe thereof, as good Chriſtians ſhould doe, but wee are carefull about earthly things as the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles uſed to doe. Some writers make mention of ſome people that goe upon all foure, I feare there are many ſuch people in <hi>England,</hi> that by grovelling upon earth and earthly things. This is the Divells policy, who labours that duſt ſhould be our meat as it is the Serpents<note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 3.14.</note> that we ſhould bee not onely <hi>filii terrae,</hi> made of the earth as indeed we are, but <hi>toti terrei</hi> altogether earthy, both in our minds and affections. But though man bee made in <hi>terra</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Pet. Lomb. Sent. lib. <hi>2.</hi> diſt. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; exterra, non tamen ad terra, nee propter terram, ſed ad coelum, &amp; propter coelum,</hi> in the earth and of the earth, yet hee is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152100:83"/>not made to the earth nor for the earth but to Heaven and for Heaven. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then lay you out your money for that which is no bread? Are wee not all ſtrangers and pilgrims in this life? if we be not we ſhall never be Citizens in the life to come? And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as worldly, ſo ſpirituall pilgrims, muſt carry nothing, but things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. The Patriark <hi>Iacob</hi> in his jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to <hi>Padan Aran</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Gen. 28.20.</note>, deſired onely bread to eate, and rayment to put on. So Gods children in their journey to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven, deſire only a <hi>viati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum,</hi> ſufficient to ſuffice them by the way. The two things that hinder us in our journey towards Heaven, are ſinne, and earthly ſuperfluity (for it is as hard<note n="o" place="margin">Mat. 19.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4</note>, for a rich man to enter into the Kingdome of Heaven, as it is for a <hi>Camell</hi> to goe through the eye of an Needle) And therefore firſt let us disburthen our ſelves of ſinne, and lay that burthen on Chriſt, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152100:84"/>then disburthen our ſelves of earthly ſuperfluity. and caſt that burthen on the poore, ſend our riches before us, that wee may the better follow after to Heaven. The heathen Oratour can tell us, that our life is<note n="p" place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cero de Sene.</note>: <hi>commorandi, non habitandi locus,</hi> a place for ſome ſhort abiding, not for a long dwelling. Wee are <hi>non habitatores terrae, ſed accolae,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">De Abrah Patr.</note>. Immates for a time, and not permanent livers. And to this purpoſe our life is called<note n="r" place="margin">Cicero.</note>, <hi>diverſorium,</hi> an Inne, and a cutthroat Inne it is, where the ſigne forward is the Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayd, but backward ſhip-wracke, where the fleſh is Hoſtice, and the Divell (too commonly) hoſt. Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony is the Cooke, drunkennes Tapſter, and wantonnes Chamberlayne, and theſe are as officious as may bee, to give entertaynment: but when the reckoning comes to bee paid, the hoaſt (the Divell) himſelfe brings in a long Bill, with an <hi>Item</hi> for this,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152100:84"/>and an <hi>Item</hi> for that ſinne, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſtands at the Barr and juſtifies all, the end is that priſon from whence,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mat. 5.26.</note> thou ſhalt not come out, untill thou haſt payd the uttermoſt farthing. Yet many ſetting their affections on that triple headed <hi>Geryon</hi> of riches, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and pleaſure, remember not the time of their reckoning which is at hand, when they will want the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious merits of their Saviour, to pay the deare price of their ſinnes. And therefore as the Birds that feed below, do build on high, ſo wee though wee live below on earth, muſt build above, and lay up our treaſure in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. <hi>Si diem mortis nostrae in mente ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemus, statim ea, quae in hoc mundo ſunt, deſpicimus,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">De modo bonè vivendi <hi>Ser. 8.</hi>
               </note>, If wee did but conſider, how ſhort a time wee have to live in this World, wee would not ſet our affections on it, but on a better. The <hi>Hedghog</hi> that hath rouled his skin full of Apples, when
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152100:85"/>hee comes to the hole, hee wipes them all of: ſo hee that hath fethered his neſt with the things of this World, yet when hee comes to his hole, hee leaves all behinde him. Naked came wee into this World, and naked ſhall wee goe out againe<note n="u" place="margin">Job. 1.21.</note>; Let us not then bee like the <hi>Raynbow,</hi> which though it ſeeme to bee in the Ayre, yet the ends tend to the earth, but rather like the <hi>Ceder</hi> that ſtretcheth forth her bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches toward Heaven. <hi>Interpoſitio terrae est cauſa Eclipſeos lunae.</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">Magir. Phiſ.</note> The Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Earth betweene the Sunne and the Moone, is the cauſe of the Eclipſe of the Moone. And the interpoſition of earthly things betweene the Sunne of righteouſnes and us, doth blind our ſpirituall eyes, that wee cannot thinke of Heaven; but are like the Moone, when wee are at the full (oftentimes) in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt oppoſition to that Sunne. As GOD ſaid unto <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Gen. 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>Exi de
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152100:85"/>terra tua,</hi> Get thee out of thy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and from thy kindred, unto a Land that I ſhall ſhew thee, ſo doth hee ſpeake unto the Church in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and to every member in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular<note n="y" place="margin">Pſal. 45 10.</note>, forget thine owne people and thy fathers houſe. This World is our Fathers houſe, the Land wherein we are borne and bread, but we muſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get our fathers houſe, forſake<note n="z" place="margin">Doctor <hi>Boys</hi> on the Epiſt. for <hi>Eaſter</hi> day.</note>, this <hi>homestall,</hi> and ſeeke for another in the ſpirituall <hi>Chanaan</hi> one to come in <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> that is above. Wee muſt ſay to the World (when it is gotten in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the cloſet of our hearts) as <hi>Amnon</hi> did<note n="a" place="margin">2 Sam. 13.15.</note>: to his ſiſter, get thee hence. And if it will not bee gone, we muſt thruſt it out, and lock the dores of our hearts, and ſhut the windowes of our affections after it. It is written of the <hi>Squerill</hi> and <hi>Badger</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Pliny.</note>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that in their neſts and dens they have two holes, one they open towards the Sunne, but ſhut the other to keepe out the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152100:86"/>bluſtering winds: ſo let us open the dores of our hearts toward the Sunne of righteouſnes, but keepe them ſhut againſt the bluſterings of this world. Wee ſhould bee like <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> veſſell which being made of virgins Wax, would keepe out the ſalt water, but receive the freſh: ſo let us refuſe the bitter waters of <hi>Iericho,</hi> and receive the waters of life. If wee affect <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> that is above, let us neglect <hi>Babilon</hi> that is below. Remember then (O man) that thou art a man, looke not downward on the earth with the eyes of thy ſoule, as beaſts doe with the eyes of their bodies. Goe not on thy belly with the Serpent, grow not with the Bramble with both ends to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the earth, but be lifted upward toward Heaven, that thou mayſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to bee a member of the Church which doth herein reſemble the Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of <hi>the Lily of the Vallies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the leaves of the <hi>Lily</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:152100:86"/>do extend outwards and bend down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, ſo the Church and the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof muſt extend their chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not onely to them that are neere, either by propinquity of neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, or affinity of kindred, but even to them that are farr off. The heart of man doth derive the heat, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the breaſt and belly, and the parts that are neere it, but even to the toes, and fingers, and the parts far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt of, ſo the members of the Church ought to extend their charity not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to them that are neere, but even no them that are farr off. The <hi>Henn</hi> (they ſay) will cover no Chickens under her wings, but her owne, or ſuch as ſhee ſuppoſeth to bee her owne; So many will make much of none, but thoſe that are of their owne kindred, as for ſtrangers there is no hope of any thing for them. Nature<note n="c" place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſtotle.</note>, in the generation of a <hi>Frogge,</hi> being af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayd that her matter will not hold out,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152100:87"/>doth beſtow ſo much on the breaſt and belly, and the parts neere the heart, that there is little left for the legges, whence it is that the belly of a <hi>Frogge</hi> is ſo large and ſwelling: ſo many feare that their ſubſtance will not hold out, they ſhall not have inough for their friends and kindred, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their donation is very ſmall for them that are farre off, I ſpeake not this, to ſtreighten the bowells of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and charity in men to their owne kindred, for in ſome they are ſtraitned too much already, in theſe degenerate dayes of ours, wherein a man may oftentimes meete with a more lively heat of affection from ſtrangers, then from their owne friends and alliyes. The Apoſtle ſaith<note n="d" place="margin">1 Tim. 5.8</note>: hee that provideth not for his owne, hee is worſe then an infidell. <hi>Coſmogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers</hi> make mention of ſome <hi>Anthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pophagi,</hi> men eaters, that live neere the <hi>Caſpian</hi> Hills, that the children uſe to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152100:87"/>eat their fathers when they grow old, that they ſhould not bee devoured of the Wormes. This cuſtome I feare may bee found among many, when as the Prophet ſpeaks<note n="e" place="margin">Ezek 5.10.</note>: the fathers eat the ſonnes, and the ſonnes eat the fathers, they oftentimes conſuming and devouring the eſtates one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The Apoſtle makes it a note of the laſt dayes<note n="f" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.3.</note>: that men ſhould bee without naturall affection. How can they bee ſpiritually affected<note n="g" place="margin">Abſal. Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all Teares.</note>, that are not naturally affected? Can they love Gods children that have no love to their owne bowells? or they be friends to their enemies, that are tirants to their friends. So that it is true that charitas <hi>inicpit</hi> in <hi>ſeipſa,</hi> charity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginns at him. Yet <hi>non deſinit in ſeipſa,</hi> it muſt not end there, but goe abroad to ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neighbours <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great<note n="h" place="margin">Fuſeb. Eccleſ. Hyſt. li. <hi>9.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> got great favour of the people, and added to the Chriſtians dayly by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding for the poore, inſomuch that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152100:88"/>the <hi>Gentiles</hi> noted the love of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans one to another, and by their chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty were ſometimes compelled to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the God of the Chriſtians. <hi>Stipis pauperum the ſaurus divitum,</hi> was the word of the good Emperour <hi>Tiberius Conſtantius</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Reuſner. Symb.</note>, The rich mans treaſure is the poore mans ſtock. It is recorded<note n="k" place="margin">Nazian in vita ejus.</note>: of S. <hi>Bazill</hi> the great, that in a famine hee did not onely give to the poore ſuch as hee had himſelfe, but exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all others to ſet open their Barnes and to doe the like. But now there are many churliſh <hi>Naballs</hi> that ſay<note n="l" place="margin">1 Sam. 25.10, 11.</note>, <hi>Who is David? and who is the ſonne of</hi> Ieſſe? <hi>there bee many ſervants now adayes that breake away every man from his Mayster. Shall I then take my bread and my water, and my fleſh that I have killed for my ſhearers, and give it unto men whom I know not whence they bee? There is many an unmercifull</hi> Dives<note n="m" place="margin">Luke 16.</note>, <hi>that will not part with a crumme, though it might make them to gayne a Crowne.</hi> For <hi>Da parva ut
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152100:88"/>magna recipias</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bazill</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">In Div. pag. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note>. He that gives little ſhall receave much. And <hi>damna lucrum,</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Div. Chryſiſt.</note> The crummes that fall from thy table are loſt, and yet not loſt if thou giveſt them to the poore, for he<note n="p" place="margin">Prov. 19.17.</note>: that hath pity on the poore lendeth to the Lord, and that which he hath given will hee pay him againe. We have few tender hearted <hi>Davids,</hi> whoſe<note n="q" place="margin">Pſal. 22.14.</note>, heart is like wax, and mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the midſt of their bowells: many like the <hi>Leviathan</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Job 41.24.</note>: whoſe heart is as firme as a ſtone, yea as hard as a ſtone, yea as hard as a peice of the nether Mil-ſtone, wee have few like them <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeakes of<note n="ſ" place="margin">Job 21.24.</note>, whoſe breaſts are full of Milke, and their bones moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened with Marrow, many like <hi>David</hi> in this, when his<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 102.3.</note>, bones were dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or burnt up, as an hearth: few that can ſay with <hi>Iob</hi> v, I have not eaten my morſell my ſelfe alone,<note n="v" place="margin">Job 31.17.</note> but the fatherles hath eaten thereof: but many that with-hold the poore from their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152100:89"/>deſire. Our Saviour Chriſt bids<note n="w" place="margin">Luke. 3.11.</note>: him that hath two coates, to impart to him that hath none, but rather we are like <hi>David</hi> in his old age, wee thinke all clothes to little to get<note n="x" place="margin">1 Kings 1.1.</note>, heat in our ſelves; We are like <hi>Iſaacks</hi> well <hi>Reho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Gen. 26 2.</note>, that ſignifyes roome, we have roome inough to receive, but when we ſhould give any thing, we are like the Well of <hi>Haran</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Gen. 29.2.</note>: that had a ſtone row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon the mouth thereof; Our hearts are made, like the dore of that hard hearted neighbour in the Goſpell<note n="a" place="margin">Luke. 11.7.</note> hard to bee opened I cannot riſe and lend, much leſſe would hee riſe and give. It is true that there are among us ſome mercifull <hi>Samaritans,</hi> good <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neliuſſes,</hi> charitable <hi>Tabithaes,</hi> and <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſes,</hi> (and God increaſe the number of them.) But all the members of the Church ſhould bee open handed and open hearted: for <hi>Aurum habet Eccleſia, non ut ſerret, ſed uteroget,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſſe.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Offic. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> The Church hath gold not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152100:89"/>to keepe but to give: we being Gods ſtewards to diſpoſe of them to them that need. I have read of ſome <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians,</hi> that ſay the cuſtome of their countrey gives nothing to the poore. I ſay not that this cuſtome is knowne in our <hi>Hoemiſphere,</hi> or come into our countrey; and yet if wee looke into the diſpoſition of many, we may find them of the nature of a ſpunge, which will eaſily take in water, but will let nothing goe without ſqueezing; their hands are dryed up like <hi>Ieroboames</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Kings 13.4.</note>, they cannot ſtretch them out to give an almes. But as the Load-ſtone draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth iron to it, ſo ſhould our charity draw the poore unto it: there are but few ſuch Loadſtones found among us. Many are rather like a kind of Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone reported to bee<note n="d" place="margin">Pliny.</note>, in <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> which hath two cornes; the one draws iron to it, the other expells it from it. Many make uſe of that corner that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pells from them. When they have need
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152100:90"/>of a poore mans helpe, then they will draw him unto them with the one cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but when their purpoſe is brought to paſſe, then they will turne <hi>alterum angulum,</hi> the other corner, and bid him be gon. Anglers uſe little Flyes to catch great Fiſhes, and many uſe poore friends to effect great matters, But they uſe them as they doe their ſhoe-hornes, to draw on ſome good turne on them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and when they have done they put them away. Poore men have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes need of the rich, and rich men have ſometimes need of the poore. And as they doe make uſe of the poore to helpe them at their need, ſo ſhould they releeve them at their need. Wee muſt put on<note n="e" place="margin">Coloſ. 3.12</note>, the bowells of mercyes, and be mercyfull<note n="f" place="margin">Luke 6.36.</note>: as our father in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is mercifull. Let us not ſhut the bowells of our affections, but rather be like the water, <hi>facile fluit in termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num alienum,</hi> it eaſily floweth into others bounds. But let us not be like
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152100:90"/>the Wells which keepe all in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as thoſe that are every man for himſelfe, and doe nothing at all for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: nor yet like to the Rivers, which water the banks onely that are neere unto them, as thoſe that extend their charity only to their kindred, nor yet like the Sea, which ſendeth forth wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters into the Rivers which returne back againe thither, as thoſe that give their gifts, as they toſſe the ball at tennys, to them that will bandy it back againe with requitall: but like the raine that falls from the Clouds in all places, ſo if we belong to the Church, we muſt ſhew our charity to the loweſt mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church: for therein the Church and the members thereof muſt reſemble the leaves of the <hi>Lily of the Valleyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is written of the <hi>Eagle</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Pliny.</note>, that ſtanding on a rock, ſhe looketh on three things, upward toward the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the Sunne, about her to the place
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152100:91"/>whether ſhe would flee, and down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward on her crooked talents: ſo muſt we looke on three things eſpecially, upward toward GOD ſetting our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections on Heaven and not on earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, about us on our neighbours, extending our charity to them: and downward on our ſelves: which I am now to ſpeake off: for Thirdly, as the leaves of the <hi>Lily</hi> are white within and without, ſo muſt the Church manifeſt the whitnes of her innocency, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there are ſome blacke <hi>Lillies,</hi> yet are the white the pureſt. The Prieſts were cloathed with white<note n="h" place="margin">Ezek. 44.17</note>: linnen cloathes, when they did enter into the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> ſignifying integrity and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of converſation, that all that will come neere the Lord, muſt be cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with thoſe white robes; If the King of <hi>Babell</hi> choſe children<note n="i" place="margin">Daniel. 1.4</note>: in whom there was no blemiſh to ſtand in his Pallace. Shall God admit any that are full of ſpots, to ſtand in the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152100:91"/>Court of Heaven? The Temple of fortune was built with the whiteſt ſtones that could be got, being fetched from <hi>Cappodocia</hi> in the Emperour <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes</hi> time, and ſhall not the Temple of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> (the Church) bee built with white ſtones, ſuch as the <hi>Patriarkes,</hi> and <hi>Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Apostles,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Zacharias</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Luke 1.6.</note>, that walked in all the Comandements, and ordinances of the Lord blameles. But how can the Church be ſayd to be white, when ſhe ſayes of her ſelfe<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sol. Song.</hi> 1.5</note>, that ſhe is blacke? S. <hi>Augustin</hi> anſwers<note n="m" place="margin">De Temp. Ser <hi>86.</hi>
               </note>: that ſhee is <hi>nigra per naturam, formoſa per gratiam,</hi> black by nature but white by grace. <hi>Nigra per inhaerens peccatum</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">In Cant Ser. 33.</note> black through ſinne that dwelleth in her, <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſa per justitiam imputatam,</hi> beautifull by Chriſts righteouſnes imputed to her. She is black as the tents of <hi>Kedar,</hi> which S. <hi>Ierome</hi> ſayes<note n="o" place="margin">Super Cant Cantic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>: doth ſignify darknes it ſelfe, but comely as the curtaines of <hi>Solomon,</hi> which were of ſilke and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broydered
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152100:92"/>with gold <hi>Aethiopiſſa non mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat colorem</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Domin. p. Oct. Epiph.</note>: the <hi>Aethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian</hi> cannot change his skin,<note n="q" place="margin">Jer. 13.23.</note> but <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeam praecaedit Aethipia peccat; exuends nigredme &amp; fidei induendo candore,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">De Temp. Ser. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note>. <hi>Aethiopia</hi> ſurpaſſeth <hi>Iudaes</hi> in this, in putting of the blacknes of ſin, and putting on the beauty of faith Some thinke<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Brightman</hi> on the Rev.</note>, S. <hi>Iohn</hi> doth deſcribe the Church when he ſayth.<note n="t" place="margin">Rev. 1.14.</note> The head and the hayre were white like ſnow and like wooll; The Church hath the whitnes of wooll, by reaſon of the ſimplicity, and innocency wherewith the Saints are endewed, which are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes in the Scripture called ſheepe, and no mervaile, for Chriſt their head is called a Lamb<note n="u" place="margin">John 1.29.</note>, and of Snow, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the whitnes thereof is not natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, but adventitiall. And as Wooll, ſo the righteouſnes of the ſaints, will quickly bee fowle and duſty of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but being waſhed in the cleane Fountaine of Chriſts bloud, it will be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152100:92"/>as white as Snow, or any thing elſe that exceedes in whitnes. But how can the Church be ſayd to bee all white? for if we take the Church generally there are many profane <hi>Eſaus</hi> crept into her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome: and if we take it ſtrictly for the multitude of beleevers; how can it then be ſayd to be all beautifull? for if the beſt of us looke on our ſelves in the glaſſe of Gods Law, we ſhall finde that we come farr ſhort of the beauty of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines. I anſwer, if the Church bee taken generally, then is her beauty like <hi>Ioſephs</hi> coat, party coloured, but if it be taken ſtrictly, then ſhe may be ſayd to bee all beautifull, though not in <hi>ſenſu diviſo,</hi> but in <hi>ſenſu compoſito.</hi> In her ſelfe<note n="w" place="margin">Doctor <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce</hi> on the Cant.</note> her ſpots are as many as <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſores, or <hi>Iobs</hi> bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but through Chriſt, ſhe becomes as beautifull as <hi>Abſalom. Ipſe qui venit ſine macula, &amp; ruga, extenſus est in tendicula, ſed propter nos, non propter ſe, ut nos faceret ſine macula, &amp; ruga</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Aust,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">De verb. Apoſt. Ser. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> he that came without ſpot, or wrinckle, was
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152100:93"/>ſtretched out upon the tenters, but not for himſelfe, but for us, to make us with out ſpot, or wrinckle. It is a cuſtome with us, that what belongs to the Brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome, the Bride hath title to: ſo the Church, hath Chriſts, her husbands, beauty imputed to her; And therefore S. <hi>Bernard</hi> notes<note n="y" place="margin">In Cant. Cantic.</note>: that the Church is rather ſayd to be <hi>dealbata,</hi> then <hi>alba,</hi> not white as having her beauty in her ſelfe, but whited, as receiving it from Chriſt. We are all Chriſtians, and in our Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme gave up our names to Chriſt Ieſus, as preſt Souldiers to fight under his Banners, but let us examine our ſelves, whether we weare our Captaines coul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, truely white. Are we like the <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Lament. 4.7, 8.</note>, purer then Snow, and whiter then Milke? or rather are there not many like them ſpoken of in the next verſe, whoſe viſage is blacker then a coale? Are there not many that would be counted white, and yet with the <hi>Camelion</hi> can turne of any couler, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152100:93"/>others like the <hi>Leopard</hi> are full of ſpots, if not groſſe <hi>Aethiopians,</hi> that cannot be waſhed white, farre from the nature of the <hi>Lily; Noahs</hi> arke was pitched<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 6.14.</note>. with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and without, the <hi>Lily</hi> is white with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and without, and ſo muſt the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church. Which manifeſts two ſorts of men not to belong to the Church: the one is of them which though they thinke themſelves to be white within, yet it cannot be perceived by their outward actions, but that they are black. They are like <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple, though it were overlayd with gold, yet was it built of craggy ſtones. But the members of the Church muſt be like the <hi>Kings</hi> daughter<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 45.13.</note>: as ſhe was all glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious within, ſo her cloathing is of wrought gold, as they muſt have a good conſcience before God, So they muſt haue a good converſation before men. Secondly, others there are that would fayne ſeeme white without, and yet within are full of gall &amp; bitternes. They
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152100:94"/>are like the <hi>Egiptian</hi> Temples; which were very faire and beautifull without, but when you come within to their <hi>ſanctum ſanctorum,</hi> you ſhal find nothing but a <hi>Crocodile,</hi> or a <hi>Serpent</hi> which they did worſhip; So they carry a faire ſhew outwardly, but let that <hi>Serpent</hi> Satan be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witch their hearts (which ſhould bee Gods holyeſt) with ſinne. The <hi>Greeke</hi> word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is a title given to Players and Jeſters, which doe reſemble the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of great men: as <hi>Roſcius</hi> was <hi>Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memnon</hi> in ſhew, though he were <hi>Roſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> in deed, they are the children of father <hi>Abraham</hi> in ſhew, but children of their father the divell indeed, they imitate Gods Saints in ſincerity, <hi>Dum Curios ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulant, &amp; Bacchanalia vivunt,</hi> they live in iniquity. Sin hath ſome of thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> makes<note n="c" place="margin">De Not. Eccl. lib <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>, to be true notes of the true Church. Firſt, for univerſality, it hath infected all the men in the World. Secondly, for antiquity it is almoſt as old as the world, beginning
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152100:94"/>in <hi>Paradice.</hi> Thirdly, for perpetuity, it will laſt untill the worlds end. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for ſucceſſion it became haereditary to all <hi>Adams</hi> poſterity, like <hi>Naamans</hi> lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy<note n="d" place="margin">2 Kings. 5.27</note>: to <hi>Gehazi,</hi> for ever, but it wants vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility, and therefore that witch (hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy) rayſeth many up to appeare to be true <hi>Samuells,</hi> when as indeed they are very divells. The hypocrit doth conſiſt of meere formalities, and <hi>eſſe videaturs,</hi> and had rather be a member of the Church viſible, then of the Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique. Whereunto ſhall I liken the men of this generation, they are like to mud-walls, though they may be white without, yet they are full of durt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; like <hi>Swanns;</hi> whoſe feathers are very white without, but their fleſh is the blackeſt of all Birds; like the elder Tree which hath a very white wood, but beares black ſtinking berries. <hi>Goliahs</hi> ſword lay hid under an <hi>Ephod,</hi> &amp; <hi>David</hi> ſaid.<note n="e" place="margin">1 Sam. 21 9.</note> There is none like that, give it me. There is nothing like the deceit of a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152100:95"/>ſeeming hypocrite. The Leproſy that was moſt white<note n="f" place="margin">Lev. 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>: was moſt danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; though <hi>Myriam</hi> would turne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet<note n="g" place="margin">Num. 12.10.</note>: yet was ſhe ſmitten with Lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy white as Snow, ſo thoſe that pretend goodnes, and doe not intend it, it is but like the leproſy that appeares outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon them. There were ſome<note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 7.15.</note>: that came in ſheepes cloathing, were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly ravening Wolves.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Hic niger eſt, hunc tu Romane caveto<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Hunc tu Christiane caveto.</l>
            </q>
            <p>He is a black pawne, in a white coate. Wherefore as <hi>Daniel</hi> ſayd to the King,<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hyſt.</hi> of <hi>Bel.</hi> v. 7.</note> O King be not deceived, <hi>viz.</hi> by the faire ſhewes of the Preiſts: ſo ſay I to theſe men, let not their faire preſence of holines, be a cover of their inward wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ednes. Let them ceaſe to be like the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>Sodome,</hi> that grow by the lake <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaltites,</hi> that had a faire ſhew without, but within were nothing but duſt, and aſhes. It was <hi>Julians</hi> policy to make his follower, ſeeme holy, that he might the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152100:95"/>better deceive, and Satan, <hi>Julians</hi> maſter maketh his followers ſeeme holy, that he may the better deceive. But they may blind the worlds eye, yet Gods eye, <hi>Qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ninime fallitur, quia minime clauditur</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
                  <hi>Bernard.</hi>
               </note>: which is alwayes open, and never ſhut, cannot be blinded. <hi>Moſes</hi> Leproſy<note n="l" place="margin">Exod 4.6.</note> in his hand, was as apparant in the eyes of God; as <hi>Vzziahs</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">2 Chron. 26 19.</note> Leproſy in his fore-head. God ſees ſecret hypocriſy, as wel as open profannes, &amp; will diſcover it, and them. <hi>Qui color albus erat, nunc eſt contrarius albo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They ſhall appeare in their perfect co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours. Wherefore, let every one endevour to be like <hi>Ezechiells</hi> booke<note n="n" place="margin">Ezech. 2.10.</note>: that was written both within and without, like the Arke<note n="o" place="margin">Exod. 25.11.</note>: that was overlayd with pure gold, both within and without: like <hi>Maries</hi> box<note n="p" place="margin">Mat. 26.7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>: that without was <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lablaſter,</hi> and within full of oyntment, and like the <hi>Lily</hi> that is white both within and without. And thus the Church appeares to be all beautifull, for to the perfecteſt beauty, is required the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152100:96"/>beſt commixtion of red, and white: ſo that the Church may be ſaid to be white and ruddy, being blanched in the white robes of innocency, &amp; guilded with the bloud of Martyrs, ſhe is a red <hi>Roſe</hi> by her Martyrs, and a white <hi>Lily</hi> by the virgin innocency of the Saints. And though ſhe ſometimes want the crown of Martyrdome, yet ſhe muſt alwayes have the white robs of innocency<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though ſhe ſeemes ſometimes not to be the red <hi>Roſe of Sharon;</hi> yet ſhee muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes be <hi>the white Lily of the Vallies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the <hi>Lily</hi> growes among Thornes, &amp; in the Church the white <hi>Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi> flouriſh among black Thornes. In <hi>Adams</hi> family there was a <hi>Cayne,</hi> as well as an <hi>Abel:</hi> in <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke there was a <hi>Cham,</hi> as well as a <hi>Shem,</hi> or <hi>Iaphet,</hi> beaſts uncleane, as well as cleane: in <hi>Abrahams</hi> houſe there was an <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> as well as an <hi>Iſack</hi> and it is no greater wonder to ſee a <hi>Iudas</hi> among Chriſts Diſciples; then it was to ſee a <hi>Saul</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">2 Sam. 19.22.</note>, among the Prophets.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152100:96"/>Wicked men in the Church are mixed with true beleevers, and the Tares muſt grow among the Wheat: for the Church is a <hi>Lily</hi> among Thornes. Which may fitly be applyed againſt the <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> that leave this <hi>Lily</hi> becauſe of the Thornes, and goe out of the Church by reaſon of ſome bad. They have a heat in them but it is a ſtrange fire, raked out of the embers of paſſion, blowne with the bellowes of pride, and ſelfe conceited<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and mayntained by the fewell of faction, which makes them at firſt to be <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>axardens,</hi> and then <hi>draco volans;</hi> Like humid bodyes <hi>facilè in alienis terminis difficultèr in ſuis continentur:</hi> they firſt croſſe the Church and then the ſeas, firſt run out of reaſon and then out of the Church. Curſed be ſuch heat; for it is cruell, O my ſoule<note n="r" place="margin">Gen 49.6.</note>, come not thou into their ſecret, be not thou united to their aſſembly. When <hi>Lot</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> fell out, <hi>Lot</hi> would needs part with him, though he told them that they were
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152100:97"/>brethren<note n="ſ" place="margin">Gen. 13.8.</note>. So thoſe <hi>Separatiſts</hi> fall out with the Biſhops of our Church, and ſay as thoſe in S. <hi>Austins</hi> time<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſtin in</hi> Pſal. 129.</note>: <hi>Sepere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus nos,</hi> let us goe out from among them. And although wee ſay to them, <hi>Servate pacem</hi> keepe the peace and love the unity of the Church, yet they will goe out from us,<note n="u" place="margin">Gen. 13.12.</note> although (I feare) of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes with <hi>Lot</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">v</hi> into <hi>Sodome,</hi> when the other with <hi>Abraham</hi> may enter into the Land of <hi>Chanaan.</hi> When Chriſt was upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth was his head, pricked with Thornes, his body was ſcourged, but<note n="w" place="margin">John 19.36</note>: not a bone of him was broken: ſo now he is in Heaven though his head be pricked with contentions (although it might bee wiſhed that it were not pricked at all) yet let us not breake his bones. We muſt not part <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas,</hi> for<note n="x" place="margin">Acts 15 37.</note>, <hi>Markes</hi> ſake, as long as wee agree in fundamentall poynts of faith, we muſt not goe out of the Church; by reaſon of ſome errors, or imperfections I wrote unto you ſaith the Apoſtle<note n="y" place="margin">1 Cor. 5.9.10</note>: not
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152100:97"/>to keepe company with fornicators: yet not altogether with the fornicators of this World, or with the covetous, or extortioners or idolators, for then muſt yee needs goe out of the World. Should <hi>Noah</hi> have forſaken the company of all wicked men, he muſt have gone out of the World; for the whole earth was corrupt and<note n="z" place="margin">Gen. 6.11.</note>: filled with cruelty, ſave onely he and his family. What S. <hi>Auſtin</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Epiſt. 48.</note>: determined againſt the <hi>Donathists;</hi> may be urged againſt theſe men, <hi>non propter malos boni deſerendi, ſed propter bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ios malitolerandi.</hi> We muſt not forſake the good for the bad, but muſt tolerate the bad for the good. The Tares muſt grow among the Wheat without a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, untill the Lord of the harveſt make a ſeperation, at the generall day of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udgment, and the <hi>Lily</hi> (the Church) muſt grow among Thornes. But as the <hi>Lily</hi> among Thornes: retaynes the whitenes and ſweetnes, ſo muſt the Church among thorny ſinners and hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152100:98"/>Chriſtians retayne her innocency And this is<note n="b" place="margin">Angelom in locum.</note>: no diſprayſe to the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous but rather their prayſe to be godly among the wicked, and not to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the thorny converſation of others but to ſhine as lights in darknes. <hi>Non mediocris eſt titulus profecto virtutis inter pravos vivere bonum, &amp; inter malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantes innocentiae retinere candorem, magis autem ſi his qui oderunt pacem, pacificum te praebeas &amp; amicum,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">In Cant. Ser. 48.</note> It is no ſmall vertue, to be good among the evill, to be innocent among the nocent, and to be peaceable among the turbulent and contentious: herein they are like the <hi>Lillies</hi> themſelves, which by their owne beauty adorne the Thornes by which they are pricked. It is no great matter to ſeeme to bee good among the good, and according to the <hi>Proverb.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Cum fueris Romae, Romano vivere more.</q>
            <p>When you are at <hi>Rome,</hi> to doe as the <hi>Romans</hi> doe, but the godly muſt reteyne
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152100:98"/>their innocency in the midſt of the tents of <hi>Kedar</hi> ſhe muſt reteyne her whitenes, for therein the Church re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembles <hi>the Lily of the Vallies.</hi> And ſo I come to the limitation of this ſecond attribute, to the ſecond ſubject (of the <hi>Vallies</hi>) <hi>I am the roſe of Sharon and the Lily of the Vallies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Church is the low <hi>Lilly of the low Vallies,</hi> which may teach humility to all the members thereof. Humility is the firſt ſtep toward Heaven, and I know not how they that, miſſe that may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend any higher. How can any thinke to thruſt into Heaven by that, that made Satan be caſt out? pride was the divells ruine, and can any thinke it ſhould be his rayſing? And that we may practiſe humility wee may learne it<note n="d" place="margin">Deſtruct. vitior.</note>: from things without us, from things we car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with us, from things about us, and from God above us. Firſt, from things without us, even from the earth it ſelfe, from whence we came and whither
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152100:99"/>we muſt: for God tells <hi>Adam</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 3.19.</note>, duſt thou art, and to duſt thou ſhalt returne. So that when thou ſeeſt the earth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thy Sepulchre. And what cauſe haſt thou to be proud? if thou conſider that the earth which is now under thy feete, ſhall ſhortly bee over above thy head? Secondly, we may learne humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from what we carry with us, even from our ſelves, if we conſider our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe into the World, our progreſſe in the World, and our egreſſe out of the World. Firſt, the ingreſſe of mans life is miſerable, he beginning his life with teares; as bewayling the miſeries of his ſucceeding ages. Secondly, the progreſſe of mans life is ſhort and tranſitory, but a<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 39.6.</note>: ſpannlong; and as ſhort as<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 90.9.</note>: a tale that is told. Thirdly, mans egreſſe is bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and terrible, and therefore death is ſayd to be<note n="h" place="margin">Ariſtot.</note>, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the King<note n="i" place="margin">Job 18.14.</note>: of terrors; And what cauſe (then) hath man to be proud, when at his birth his conception is deteſtable, in his life his
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152100:99"/>converſation culpable, and at his death his diſſolution terrible? Thirdly, wee may learne humility from men about us, when we conſider that many of our brethren are poore, or lame, or blind or miſerable, and we are made of the ſame matter in the ſame mould: and deſerve it as well as they. And therefore what cauſe haſt thou to be proud; thou being as ſubject to thoſe calamities as they, &amp; knoweſt not how ſoone thou mayſt fall into them? Laſtly, we may learne humility from God above us. God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſiſteth the proud<note n="k" place="margin">1 Pet, 5.5.</note>: but giveth grace to the humble. The humble are in Gods eyes as Starres are in mans, though they ſeeme little yet they are great. <hi>Quanto quis humilior fuit de ſeipſo, tanto major erit in conſpectu dei</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Austin</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Ad fratr in Erem. Ser. <hi>7</hi>
               </note>: how much the more humble a man is in his owne eyes, ſo much the greater is he in the ſight of God. We bow our ſelves at the example of ſome great perſon, or if we were to goe in at ſome low dore, or
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152100:100"/>if a ſword hang over our heads, and we under it. But the ſword of Gods wrath hangs over the proud, and we are to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in by the low dore. Chriſt, who hath left us an example of humility. To be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have our ſelves humbly <hi>est Christum ſcire imitari,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bazil</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">De Abdicat rerum.</note> is to imitate Chriſt; but to carry ones ſelfe proudly <hi>est Diabolo ſe ſimilem praebere,</hi> that is to be like the Divell. And now I am ſure thou haſt no cauſe to bee proud, except thou meaneſt to be conformable to the divell, and abhominable to God. To conclude without any further applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (becauſe what hath beene ſpoken of this part hath (for the moſt part) beene by way of application. Let every true <hi>Iſraelite</hi> fill his <hi>Omer</hi> with this ſpirituall <hi>Mannah,</hi> Let every one take a poſy of theſe Flowers home with him, nay let him compoſe himſelfe (as it were): poſy of them. And let us all ſhew that we have the ſweetnes of the <hi>Roſe,</hi> and the whitenes of the <hi>Lily,</hi> by innocency
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152100:100"/>in ourſelves, and charity to others, that Chriſt that feedeth<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sol. Song</hi> 6.3.</note> among the <hi>Lillies</hi> may take delight in us, and accept us for his Spouſe to live with him for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. <hi>Which God grant we may all doe for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake our onely Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour. To whom with thee, O Father, and thy bleſſed Spirit, be aſcribed all Honour and Glory, might and Majesty now and for ever,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:152100:101"/>
            <p>Imprimatur hic liber cui titulas est (<hi>(The Roſe and the Lily)</hi> modò intra ſex men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes proximè ſequentes typis mandetur.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Ex aedibus Fulham. <date>
                     <hi>Iuly, 11. 1638.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Sa. Baker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
